<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods house, with the nature, and use thereof, as it ought to be understood and respected by Christians under the Gospel. / By Simon Gunton M. of Art.</title>
            <author>Gunton, Simon, 1609-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85778</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868057</idno>
  <idno type="VID">170261</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248516042</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1684_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209167</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868057</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99868057e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85778)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 210:E1684[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods house, with the nature, and use thereof, as it ought to be understood and respected by Christians under the Gospel. / By Simon Gunton M. of Art.</title>
                  <author>Gunton, Simon, 1609-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 130 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Dring, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the George in Fleet-street, near Cliffords-Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October]. 2.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church buildings --  Vandalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170261:1"/>
            <p>GODS HOUSE, WITH The nature, and use thereof, as it ought to be understood and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected by Christians under the Gospel.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Simon Gunton</hi> M. of Art.</p>
            <q>Par domus est Coelo, sed minor est Domino. <bibl>
                  <hi>Martial. lib. 8. Ep. 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Offendi quamvis quosdam suspicer his quae dicimus; sed quia veritas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis quàm offensio cogitanda est, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam. <bibl>
                  <hi>Salvianus de Guber. l. 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Dring,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the Signe of the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet-street,</hi> near <hi>Cliffords-Inne,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170261:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170261:2"/>
            <head>To The Illustrious ESME, <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Richmond</hi> and <hi>Lenox,</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi> Lord <hi>Darneley,</hi> Baron of <hi>Leighton, Settrington, &amp;c.</hi> His Grace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou being now, in your tender years, to think of erecting the building of an holy and religious life; may your Grace vouchsafe me leave to present you with one stone towards the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof. Which stone (to speake without glory or ostentation, in my own handy-worke) is not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Sun, endued with these two
<pb facs="tcp:170261:3"/>properties, of Light, and Heat; with the one, to illuminate your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in the nature of Gods house; with the other, to warm you affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and inflame your devotion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. If you shall be carefull of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this stone into your foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the structure, with all the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereto belonging, will the more happily proceed; for God, whose house you love,
<note place="margin">Psal. 20.2</note> will sond you helpe from his Sanctuary, and strengthen you out of Sion, where by you shall be able unto, and succesfull in every good work. I cannot, but Joresee, and therefore take the boldness to forewarn you, that in this distracted age wherein you are fallen, you may meet with many Architects, who will quarrel with this stone, as offensive and scandalous, and so propound o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther models unto you; But, <hi>My Lord,</hi> the wisest, and most religious Master-builders have gone this way, making the house of God a principal part of their religion, seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods Oracles there, and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting after the waters,
<note place="margin">Chap. 47.1.</note> which (like those in <hi>Ezekiel</hi>) issue forth from
<pb facs="tcp:170261:3"/>thence, they have been refreshed, and strengthened in the progress of an holy life.</p>
            <p>The presumption of Dedicating this poor Treatise to your tender hand, is, in some measure, to testifie my obligations to your most Noble Parents; in whose debt, being as deeply engaged, as <hi>Philemon</hi> was in St. <hi>Pauls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 19.</note> to owe them even my own selfe, for their vouchsafing me an harbour, when I was well nigh sunk by the common tempest; I could do no less, then offer as a weak testimony of my due thankefulnesse unto them, in you their Sonne, and hopefull heire, as of their Estate, so of their Vertues. Your favour therefore, My Lord; I humbly crave in the acceptance, diligence in the perusall, and observance of what is thus presented; And this. upon an humble assurance given, that what shall be wanting on my part, in this, or any other actuall endeavours to serve you, shall be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by my daily prayers for you, (that, as God hath dignified you with the title of worldly <hi>Grace,</hi> so he
<pb facs="tcp:170261:4"/>would be pleased to sanctifie you with his <hi>Grace</hi> which is heavenly, adding to your shining in wordly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ability to shine in an holy life, that hereafter you may shine in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory) as, My Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces most humbly devoted servant <hi>S. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170261:4"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader, these Books fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are Printed for, and sold by <hi>Thomas Dring</hi> at the George in <hi>Fleetstreet</hi> near <hi>Cliffords</hi> Inne.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ARtamenes,</hi> or the Grand <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> an excellent new Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, written by that famous Wit of <hi>France, Monsieur de Scudery,</hi> Governour of <hi>Nostre-dame,</hi> and now englished by <hi>F. G.</hi> Esq; Fol.</p>
            <p>The Continuation of <hi>Artame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> or the Grand <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent new Romance, being the third and fourth Parts; written by that Famous Wit of <hi>France, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur de Scudery,</hi> Governour of <hi>Nostre-dame:</hi> and now Englished by <hi>F. G.</hi> Esq; Fol.</p>
            <p>The third Volume of <hi>Artame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> or the grand <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent new Romance, being the fifth and fixth parts, written by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous wit of <hi>France, Monsieur de Scudery,</hi> Governour of <hi>Nostre-dame</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170261:5"/>and now englished by <hi>F. G.</hi> Esq; Fol. 1654.</p>
            <p>The fourth Volume of <hi>Artame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> or the Grand <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent new Romance, being the seventh and eighth parts, written by that famous Wit of <hi>France, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur de Scudery,</hi> Governor of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre-dame,</hi> and now englished by <hi>F. G.</hi> Esq; Fol.</p>
            <p>The fifth Volume of <hi>Artamenes,</hi> or the Grand <hi>Cyrus</hi> that excellent new Romance, being the ninth and tenth parts, written by that famous Wit of <hi>France, Monsieur de Scu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery,</hi> Governour of <hi>Nostre-dame,</hi> and now englished by <hi>F. G.</hi> Esq; Fol.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> or the Illustrious <hi>Bassa,</hi> an excellent new Romance, the whole work in fourparts, written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>Monsieur de Scudery,</hi> and now englished by <hi>Henry Cogan</hi> Gent. Fol.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cloelia,</hi> an excellent new Romance written by that famous Wit of <hi>France, Monsieur de Scudery,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Nostre-dame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The second Volume of <hi>Cloelia</hi> that excellent new Romance, written by that famous Wit of <hi>France, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur
<pb facs="tcp:170261:5"/>de Scudery,</hi> Governour of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre-dame,</hi> and now englished by <hi>J. D.</hi> Fol. 1656.</p>
            <p>The History of Philosophy by <hi>Thomas Stanley</hi> Esq; containing those on whom the attribute of the wise was conferred, with divers Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</p>
            <p>The second Volume of the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Philosophy by <hi>Thomas Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> Esq; Fol.</p>
            <p>The History of <hi>Suethland</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by <hi>Iohn Fowler,</hi> illustrated with divers Figures, Fol.</p>
            <p>The twelfth part of the Reports of Sir <hi>Edwara Coke;</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>The Reports of that Reverend and learned Judge Sir <hi>Richard Hutton</hi> Knight, Fol.</p>
            <p>The Reports of Judge <hi>Owen,</hi> in Fol.</p>
            <p>The Reading upon the Statute of the thirteenth of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Chapter 1.7. touching Bankrupts, learnedly and amply explained, by <hi>Iohn Stone</hi> in 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
            </p>
            <p>Anti-Socinianism, or a brief expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of some places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the confutation of certain grosserrors, &amp; Socinian Heresies, latly
<pb facs="tcp:170261:6"/>published by <hi>Will. Pinchion</hi> Gent. Also a brief description of the lives and true relation of the death of the authors, promoters, propagators, and chief disseminators of this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian Heresie; how it sprung up, by what meanes it spread, and when and by whom it was first brought into <hi>England</hi> by <hi>N. Chewney M.A.</hi> and Minister of Gods word. in 4<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Cragg</hi> against <hi>Tombes,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Infants Baptism. in 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
            </p>
            <p>The life and death of <hi>Freeman Sands,</hi> Esq; by <hi>Robert Boreman,</hi> B. D. in 4<seg rend="sup">o</seg> sticht.</p>
            <p>An Exhortation for desperate sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, written by the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord Viscount <hi>Grandison</hi> Prisoner in the Tower.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at the Assises at <hi>Huntington</hi> by <hi>Iohn Gaule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sand</hi>'s Psalms in 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg> large.</p>
            <p>Good Thoughts for every day in the week by <hi>D.</hi> S. in 24.</p>
            <p>Modern Policies taken from <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel, Borgia,</hi> and other choise Authors, by an eye-witness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mirza,</hi> A Tragedy really acted in <hi>Persia,</hi> written by <hi>Robert Barron</hi> Esq; in 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg> large.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170261:6"/>
            <p>Five new Playes written by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Broom</hi> in 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg> large.</p>
            <p>Poems, <hi>Amorous, Lusorie,</hi> moral and Divine, written by <hi>Edward Sherburn</hi> Esq; in 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg> large.</p>
            <p>Poems by <hi>Robert Barron</hi> Esq; 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg> large.</p>
            <p>Poems by <hi>William Hammon</hi> Esq;</p>
            <p>An Apology for <hi>Paris,</hi> written by <hi>Robert Baron</hi> Esq;</p>
            <p>A Catalogue of the Lords Knights and Gentlemen that have compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their estates, with the sums that payed their Commpositions.</p>
            <p>The second part of <hi>Massaniello,</hi> his body taken out of the Town-ditch, and solemnly buried, A Continuation of the Tumult: The Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> made <hi>Generalissimo,</hi> taken prisoner by young <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> the end of the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by <hi>I. Howell</hi> Esquire.</p>
            <p>The naturall and experimentall History of Winds <hi>&amp;c.</hi> written in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine by the Right Honorable <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Lo, Verulam,</hi> Viscount Saint <hi>Alban,</hi> translated into english by <hi>R. G.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Letters of Affaires, Love and
<pb facs="tcp:170261:7"/>Courtship, written to severall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Honour and quality, by the exquisite pen of <hi>Monsieur de Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> a Member of the famous <hi>French</hi> Academy established at <hi>Paris,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glished by <hi>Iohn Davis</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>The Law of Conveyances, show<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the nature, kinds, and effects of all manner of Assurances, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to sue out and prosecute all manner of Writs, by <hi>Iohn Herne</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>A Panegyrick of the Queene of <hi>Swedland.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 8. line 11. then, read there. 22. l. 11. places. r. palaces. 27 in the Margine r. <hi>Petrarch Ep.</hi> 59. l. 17. before, r. under. 120. l. 14. hearts, r. hats.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170261:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccles. 5.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Keepe thy foot when thou goest to the house of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>KING <hi>Solomon,</hi> as he was <hi>Structor Templi,</hi> the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Temple, so is hee <hi>Instructor ad Templum,</hi> an instructer unto the Temple, teaching us here, how to prepare and qualifie our selves in our addresses to that holy place, <hi>Custodi pedem, &amp;c. Keep thy foot, &amp;c.</hi> Some perhaps will thinke of this text in these present dayes,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 18.14.</note> as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> thought of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> as if the line reached not unto them, and so with a spirit of evill affection they will reject it, as the Devill did our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.26.</note>
               <hi>What have we to doe with thee?</hi> but with this difference, that, whereas the Devill said, Art thou come to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>us before</hi> the time? they say, Art thou come to torment, and trouble <hi>us after</hi> the time? Now that the Law, and ceremonies are aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170261:8"/>the types, and figures fulfilled, why should any disturb the minds of men with Temples, or any services therein to be performed? But such must know that this text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture lives still, extends it selfe unto us, and is written for our instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as I hope will appeare in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance of it.</p>
            <p>And, by the way, the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Penman may add much to the confirmation of this truth. For <hi>Solomon</hi> may be looked upon, as a morall writer, seeing all his writings clearely seem to us, as of perpetuall necessity, and obligation: wherein he differeth from the other writers of the old Testament: <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> wrote of many things historical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as done before, of many types, and ceremoniall services to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished, and fulfilled in after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, when their substance (Christ) should appeare; the Prophets also foretold many things which should come to passe: But <hi>Solomon</hi> not so, his writings, (those which Divine Providence hath preserved to these our dayes, in his bookes of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, Ecclesiastes,</hi> and <hi>Canticles</hi>)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170261:8"/>have little, (if any thing at all) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Histories, Types, or Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but consist of such matter as is morall, and not to be out of date, in any age, from the first publication thereof, to the worlds end. Whence we may conclude, that like our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's <hi>Vigilate, Mar.</hi> 13.37. this text is spoken to all, even to us under the Gospel, <hi>Custodi pedem, &amp;c. Keep thy foot when thou goest into the House of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In prosecuting of the words we shal observe this method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To speake of <hi>Gods house,</hi> simply by it selfe.</item>
               <item>2. Of our accesse thereunto im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in the word <hi>goest,</hi> When thou goest.</item>
               <item>3. Of the manner of our access, how it ought to be done im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in <hi>Keepe thy foot.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The first thing is Gods house Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the enemie of God, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath ever been busie to raise disputes, and contentions about things pertaining to Gods service: Amongst the rest, the house of God (by his secret inflammations, &amp; sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions) hath been the subject of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170261:9"/>much controversie, some conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding against the necessitie; others, against the dignity thereof: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was charged by God, to shew his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries, the house, that they might be ashamed of their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: So shall I (I trust by Gods help, and direction) attempt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present unto this present age, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our Christian Churches; that if mens hearts be any thing capable of being affected with shame, they may so be, for their vile opinion of, and contemptuous carriage towards, these sacred buildings. Here then we shall take into consideration two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Necessity.</item>
               <item>2. The Dignity of Gods House, as it is by the good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God established for his Churches benefit under the Gospel.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the necessity, this is not on Gods part, he having no need of any such house here on earth, no, nor of any in heaven neither, wherein to shroud his Divine Majestie; but the necessity of houses for God here on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170261:9"/>earth, is on our part; as God himselfe hath been pleased to manifest, and confirme to the world by clear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration of his Wisedome through many generations. For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God, for a long time, suffered his people to be without a temple, and put it not into any of their hearts to build him one, but every one served him in their own houses, or built altars unto God in such places as themselves thought fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; yet, when once God had brought his people out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and gathered them into an entire bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he appoynted them to build him a tabernacle; which still, was but an ambulatory, or moving house, and to continue for a time: untill the dayes of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 12.10, 11.</note> when the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Israell was settled, and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi> in their quiet possession, then would God have a more fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and immoveable habitation to be erected. To this refers that 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.6, 7. That God dwelt not in any house, since he brought the children of Israel out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> unto that day, but walked in a tent, and taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle: And spake not a word to any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170261:10"/>of the tribes of Israel to build him an house: But now that God, by his most wise providence, had fitted the time, the place, and the person, for this worke, then, and not before, would he have his house established in a fixed place, and upon a more solid foundation.</p>
            <p>This Temple of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> sustai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning its fate in severall successive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and at length arriving at its pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, our Christian Churches, (as it were by an hereditary right) have succeeded thereunto, in its rightes and priviledges: Seeing then the wisedome of God hath thought it necessary that there should be Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the world. Why should any man, by thinking them unnecessary, dare to seem wiser then God?</p>
            <p>The necessity of Churches may be illustrated by these particulars.</p>
            <p>First, that they are necessary for the more open declaration, &amp; publick manifestation of Gods religion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> &amp; the several truths appertaining there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. No sooner had God given his people a law, and rules for his service, but the next thing he appointed them, was the providing a certaine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170261:10"/>place, wherein his service was to be performed, and where his people might serve him in a publike way: Not any longer to serve him in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; or onely in private families, (every one performing divine offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, accordingly as they were taught, either by naturall illumination, or paternall education) but by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitive rules, and precepts, in a place elected, and chosen by God himself. Which publike administration of divine service is a strong argument for the truth, and sincerity thereof: therefore our Saviour, to vindicate his word from suspition of falshood,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 18.20.</note> tels <hi>Pilate,</hi> that he spake openly to the world, hee ever taught in the synagogue, and in the temple, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Jewes</hi> alwaies resorted, and in secret he said nothing. In like manner S. <hi>Paul,</hi> before Festus,
<note place="margin">Act. 26.26</note> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the sufferings of Christ, that they were not done in a corner, but in a publike place, and at a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick time; where, and when they might be witnessed by a generall concourse of people.</p>
            <p>Truth is alwaies qualified with an holy ambition of publick view,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170261:11"/>when falshood in a sneaking way seekes after private opportunities: Truth loves the light, falshood de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires darknesse.
<q>(Noctem peccatis, et fraudibus objice nubem.)
<note place="margin">Hor.</note>
               </q> least by the light it should bee discovered. Truth comes boldly <hi>in aream</hi> into Gods theatre, when fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood creepes into private houses, and then scatters her poyson: for so the Apostles describeth the practise of false teachers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Advers. Val. mihi. pag.</hi> 643.</note> and seducers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. that they creep into houses. But <hi>Tertullian</hi> was well resolved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and so resolves us, <hi>Abscondat se serpens quantum potest, totamque sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiam in latebrarum ambagibus torqueat,</hi> Let the serpent conceale himselfe as much as he can, and writhe or insinuate his wisedome in the concavities of his secret lurking places, <hi>nostrae columbae domus sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, etiam in aed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus semper a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertis, et ad lucom,</hi> the house of our dove is an honest house, alwaies with open buildings, and to the light; <hi>nihil ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas erubescit, nisi solummodò ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scondi,</hi> Truth blusheth at nothing, but to be concealed: thus <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170261:11"/>To whom if we may joyne the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie of an heathen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>mihi. p.</hi> 23</note> that of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoras</hi> in <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> will fit close and clancular seducing spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, although he was ignorant of the true God, his worship, and temple, yet supposing his religion to be true he describes the nature of such as sought to withdraw the <hi>Athenians</hi> from it, that they were <hi>Latebrosa et lucifuga natio, in publico muta, in an gulis garrula templa ut bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta despiciunt,</hi> a lurking and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hating nation, mute in publick, stre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous in corners, despising temples. This charge I say may be laid upon schismaticall, and seducing spirits under the Gospell, it being as fit for them, as their cloaths are for their backs.</p>
            <p>And yet this does not cast the least ray of approbation upon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, and falshood, though it prosper so farre, as sometimes to get into the temple and to expell truth from thence, which is now compelled to change fortunes, and to betake it self <hi>ad crypta,</hi> to secret places, &amp; comers, and glad of that too, rather then to be extinct, whilst falshood with an
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170261:12"/>open andacious face appeareth like an angel of light, railing &amp; inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against truth, boasting it selfe of that which it is farre from. Such changes have been seen in the world: the holy altar may be contemned, and neglected,
<note place="margin">2 King. 16.</note> whilst one from Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mascus shall have the favour to be employed: falshood may possesse the pulpit, and truth for a time be put to silence. The people of God may sometimes be forced to assemble themselves in corners, and secret pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, like the Disciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.19. for fear of their enemies, and yet their way of worship, and serving of God, is honest, and true for all that.</p>
            <p>Neither does this justifie the ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous religion of the heathen, who have their diabolicall services (for their idols are no better then devils) performed in their temples,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.20.</note> as so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, and publikely, as Gods ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is in his house: for the devill is but <hi>Simia Dei</hi> Gods ape and in this strives to imitate God, to have all things performed to him as they are to God himselfe, in his house: And yet falshood is falshood, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so publike, though done in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170261:12"/>light, yet it is not one jot removed from a deed of darknesse. And let these things happen as it shall please God to permit, still the divine truths of God, leading men in the wayes of saving health, must be publike, at such times, and in such places as God shall ordaine and for which purpose there is a necessity of Churches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Churches are necessary for unity, which is an essentiall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the Church, <hi>Caut.</hi> 6.9. not that the whole Catholick Church dispersed in severall Countryes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the earth, should ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily convene into one place (which cannot possibly be effected) but that every particular congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods people, whom hee hath gathered into one City, or society should have a Church to assemble themselves in, to the service of God, for the representation of that Unity which the Church in generall hath appendent to it: As there is U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in God, so is there in his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as concerning the substance of it: One Lord, one Faith, <hi>&amp;c. Eph.</hi> 4.5. And consequently there ought to be unity of persons in the house of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170261:13"/>God, all particular persons to be then present, with one accord, as one man, to worship this one God, and to professe this one faith. Insomuch that whosoever shall (in a schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall way) withdraw himself from the publicke assembly of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in his house, does thereby dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime his interest in the Unity of Gods Church. Whether or no hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men have had any apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this Unity, I will not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; but sure I am, some of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser, and more religious even amongst them, have thought it necessary to serve their Gods at all times <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Isocr. ad Demon.</note> but especially then, when the city was assembled for that purpose: which we may take with better assurance from a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian pen,
<note place="margin">Ignat. ad Magnes.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. &amp;c. All of you as one man, repair to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. Nor are we destitute of Apostolicall precepts, which may adde to the confirmation of this, for the Apostle exhorts us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. that we forsake not the assembling of our selves together, as the manner of some is. As therefore the Apostle else where asserteth the Unity of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170261:13"/>natural body, notwithstanding that it is compacted of many members, So the convention of many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular persons in Gods house, consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuteth one body of an assembly; whereby the Universall Church is represented, as an Epitome of the greater Volume; or the City Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem purtrayed in the compasse of a tile by the prophet <hi>Ezekiel. Chap.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>Thirdly: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Churches are necessary for the corroboration, and strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of prayer: for, where many are gathered together to pour forth one prayer to God with a full torrent of devotion, the conjunction of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny must needs prevaile the more strongly with him; for seeing Gods will not deny the request of one sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle person praying in private, much lesse will he deny the prayers of a multitude in his house. And to this prevalency of prayer in the Church, something more may be added from the nature of the place, not, as if the place it selfe, did, or could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre any operative vertue to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but in regard of Gods acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who (without question) is more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170261:14"/>inclinable to heare such prayers as are made in his house (it being the place upon which his Name is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and which himself hath been pleased to style, <hi>The house of prayer</hi>) than in any other place whatsoever.</p>
            <p>Neither doth it gainsay, that God heareth prayers in private, as our Saviour prescribeth our duty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and promiseth audience at Gods hands;
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.6.</note>
               <hi>Enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut the door, pray to thy Father which is in secret, and thy Father which seeth in secret, himselfe shall reward the openly:</hi> for, if God do thus 'tis his mercy: And must his mercy prejudice himselfe? Must he be affronted by us because he carries a clear brow to private devotions? Must our eye be evill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is good? Must Gods publike be disparaged, and levelled with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places because God heareth us in our private closets? I would not willingly have religious duties to jarre one with another, Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are odious, &amp; most of all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous in matters of religion: yet so far as they may be innocent, and free from casting the least blemish upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170261:14"/>private devotion, publick prayer is to have the precedency: Many are to be preferred before one. Therfore, as <hi>Eliah</hi> upon this ground, offered to the Priests of <hi>Baal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18.25.</note> because they were many, though indeed their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion was worse then his, how much more then may the prayers of many being offered to the true God, be preferred before the prayer of any single person in private, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected before it? Besides, the more effectuall prevailing with God by prayer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lyserus in conten. Harm. Chem. Col.</hi> 166.</note> which cannot be <hi>tanto effectu quanto in caetu Ecclesiastico,</hi> with so powerful effect as in a Churchassem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: Seeing that <hi>Propter reverenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am loci, or ationes fierent ibi magis exaudibiles ex devotione or antium,</hi> saith <hi>Aquinas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12<seg rend="sup">ae</seg> 102. 4.2.</note> For the reverence of the place (that is, the relation which it hath unto God, and the respect which God beareth unto it) prayers are there more easi to be heard,
<note place="margin">Gerson de vit. Cler.</note> from the devotion of the supplicants. And reason it selfe may prompt us to conceive no lesse, if like reasonable men we will but hearken unto it, that when Gods work is done in Gods place, and according to Gods
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170261:15"/>mind, it must needs find a fairer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance at Gods hand: Publick prayers in Gods house, having Gods stamp more perfectly upon them, they must needs passe for the more currant coine in his sight.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Churches are necessary for the signification, and representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of higher things, to wit of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly. It hath been Gods ordinary way (whilst men have lived in the world, and in the flesh) to teach so as is most infinuating, and percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to frail nature, and that is, <hi>Per ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pica ad vera,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 18</note>
               <hi>per temporalia ad aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, per carnalia ad spiritualia, per terrena ad coelestia:</hi> by typicall things leading us to true things, by temporall things to eternall things, by carnall things to spirituall things,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Psal.</hi> 27 4.</note> and by earthly things to heavenly things. <hi>Terrenis documen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Deus ad se deducit,</hi> God draweth us to himselfe by earthly documents saith Mr. <hi>Calvin.</hi> And of this nature is the Church, and house of God here on earth; this the type, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove in heaven, the substance. The temple of Jerusalem, Gods first fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed house, may seeme to have a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170261:15"/>typicall relation to Gods house in heaven, <hi>à parte post,</hi> as it was made, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a representative of that which was before it, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of heavens created from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. <hi>Wisd</hi> 9.8. Or, <hi>a parte ante</hi> as it was a praecursory figuration of heaven, as it shall succeed to the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of Gods people, when these earthly houses of God, with all earthly things shall arrive at their eternal period, Whence the Apostle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9 24. calleth the temple, &amp; in it our Christian Churches, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, figures of the true: And what can be more plaine? <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> (in the place cited before) va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries a little from this yet declareth it significantly enough: God (saith he) had 2. houses under the law, the tabernacle which was moveable, and the temple which was immoveable: the tabernacle was a type of the Church militant, the temple, of the Church triumphant.</p>
            <p>And to that temple of Jerusalem do our Christian Churches succeed, in being types, and figures of that building not made with hands, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the heavens. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. Doe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170261:16"/>we see then our christian temples, fairly built, decently adorned, and beautified? Doe we see them repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with militant saints, worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and resounding his praises? as our Saviour told Nathanael, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.50. we shall see greater things then these, Gods true, &amp; heavenly house, shining with the glory of God, and of the Lambe where the triumphant Saints sing,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.23.</note> Alleujah's to the praise of God for ever, and ever.</p>
            <p>As then it is not for men to stay their contemplation here at Gods earthly house, but to carry it further to the house of God which is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, so neither is it for them, so to look upon the substance, as to neglect the shaddow, which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as a methodicall way of proceeding in the pursuance of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly salvation And let the world look to it, least the slighting, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning of the figure, prove to the overthrow, and miscarriage in the fruition of the substance. These things, soberly weighed, will gaine assent to the necessity of Churches.</p>
            <p>Now because it is not to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that this necessity should bee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170261:16"/>supplyed after a miraculous manner by God himselfe, as if he should send his houses from heaven, or make them to arise out of the earth, but his will herein is to be promoted by the devotion of men, for
<q>Nos jussa capessere fas est.</q> God may command, but it is men that must put his commands in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: We shall therefore examine the auxiliaries by which this necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Churches is to bee supplyed. Where wee shall take a survey of three sorts of men.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Builders.</item>
               <item>2. Prophaners, or destroyers.</item>
               <item>3. Repairers, of the House of God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the builders, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we cannot but thinke them highly accepted with God himselfe, and that hee lookes upon their benevolence with a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aspect, if we shall trace the good pleasure of God herein, since the first revelation of all: for, as soone as Gods mind to have an house was made knowne to the Israelites, and God had issued forth his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for their contribution of such materialls as they had,
<note place="margin">Exod: 35.</note> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170261:17"/>were fitting for the worke, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did it readily.
<note place="margin">Exod. 36.6.</note> And such were their redundant liberality at that time, that they brought more then enough; insomuch, that <hi>Moses</hi> was constrained to make, as it were, a statute of Mortmaine, to restraine the peoples liberality, that they should bring no more. Wee shall hardly find amongst us Christians a a parallel to this: How farre are we (or at least would bee) of having a surplusage of contribution towards Gods House? The Israelites were not so open handed, but we are as close fisted; their excesse was not so much, but our defect would be as great, if the building of a Church were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to us. Not so with the devout people of God, when the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle had run its race, and the time of its dissolution was now at hand: for King <hi>David,</hi> out of an holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, that Gods house should be inferiour to his, and that he should dwell in an house of Cedar, and the ark of God remain within curtaines, did therefore resolve, to have it otherwise: to see what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation of mind he suffered out
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170261:17"/>of an holy zeal for a place for this tabernacle,
<note place="margin">Psal. 132.</note> that he bound himselfe with an oath, he would not goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own house, nor climbe up into his bed, untill he had brought God himself also to his resting place: But now his devotion would travell a further stage in making provision for a better house, one that should be permanent, and more magnificent, thereupon he made those large pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, as are recorded in the 22. and 29. Chapters of the first book of the Chronicles.</p>
            <p>And although this holy devotion attained not to its wished effects, for <hi>Davids</hi> owne hand to accomplish the work, God having decreed other wise, in regard <hi>Davids</hi> hand had shed much bloud, yet was it highly pleasing and acceptable unto God, who commended him for having it in his heart. 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 8 18.</p>
            <p>Unto <hi>David</hi> succeeded <hi>Salomon</hi> his son, who was encouraged by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>David,</hi> &amp; the appoyntment of God himselfe, to the building of the temple which he finished in the space of seven years, although he was thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years in building an house for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170261:18"/>himself: the reason whereof, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecturable of it selfe, as well as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by <hi>Josephus,</hi> that <hi>Salomon</hi> was more active, and zealous to goe on with Gods house, than his own, therefore he imployed more men for the more quick dispatch. How little conformity to this holy zeale of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> is to be found in these latter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the world? How quickly can we rear up stately houses &amp; places for our selves? How carefull are we to consult with architects, &amp; to employ workmen of all sorts to dispatch our own houses? but, if a Church were to be built, we double and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the prolongation: In so much (to our shame be it spoken) that if any building goes but slowly forward we say proverbially, it goes on like Church worke. But if we did consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that God is still the same God, and that there is still the same gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall end, to wit, the glory, and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, &amp; the same obligations lying upon us, as was upon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Salomons</hi> dayes, we would surely preferre holy devotion before worldly pompe, Gods service before worldly necessities, feeding-places for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170261:18"/>our soul, before sleeping places for our bodies, and so proceed with more vigour, and expedition in God's, then our own dwellings.</p>
            <p>This act of building an house for God, may more particularly be considered, as an act</p>
            <p>First of devotion; it being an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent signall, a clear light discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, an inward fervour and heat of holy devotion towards the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods worship, and service, when men are forward in erecting an house for that use.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as an act of gratitude, and thankfulnesse, by making a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution unto God, for those mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold blessings, and for that portion of worldly goods which he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to bestow. Such gratitude we find in <hi>Abraham,</hi> who no sooner received a promise from God that his seed should possesse the land of Canaan, but he builds an altar there <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.7. And the like in <hi>Jacob,</hi> who, when he hath covenanted with God, and expressed the conditions on Gods part, of Gods keeping him in the way he should goe, giving him bread to eat, and raiment to put
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170261:19"/>on, so that he might come againe to his fathers house in peace, amongst the obligations on his part, this was one, The stone which he had set up should be Gods house. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22. The same resolution of gratitude to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God we find also in <hi>Moses,</hi> who, in the name of all <hi>Israel,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth this, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.2. He is my God, and I will prepare him an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation. So great a mercy was it for God to be their God, and so highly did <hi>Moses</hi> account of it, that he thought the preparing him an house was the best requitall. In <hi>Davids</hi> time, <hi>David</hi> himself &amp; his captains, having atchieved (through the help of God) many victories, What har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest should God reap of those fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours but the contribution of much of those spoyles which they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, towards his house. 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.27? And if our hearts were touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any true desire of being thankfull to God, and of honouring him with our substance,
<note place="margin">Prov. 3.9.</note> who hath so much honoured and enriched us with his worldly blessings; this of contributing towards an house to his name, and for his service, is a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170261:19"/>dable way, <hi>Melius est hoc facere quàm repositis opibus incubare.</hi> Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is to doe this, then to hover o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our wealth in our private chests: Thirdly: we may look upon it, as an act of wisedome, and prudence: What greater wisedome then to promote Gods service? wherein <hi>Salomons</hi> wisedom shined more glorious then in all his externall dispensations: and as if this were the principall end for which God made him so wise, they are joyned together by <hi>Hiram</hi> king of <hi>Tyre,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.12. And also in point of prudence, what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then for a man to provide for his own good, by first making pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision for God? He that would esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish his own house, let him first take care for an house for God, and his desires shall have a sure and full accomplishment, whereof <hi>David</hi> received a promise from God. 2. Sam. 7.11. <hi>The Lord telleth thee, that he will make thee an house.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These things were done (as we may say) in the morning of religion; and religious ages sucessively fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, have not neglected to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them: but we in the evening, are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170261:20"/>so much declined from the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary piety of our forefathers, that the sparks of devotion towards Gods service, of thankfulnesse to God for his benefits, of wisedome, and prudence for our own Good, lye buried in the ashes of impiety, ingratitude, and improvidence, and I fear, utterly extinct, in regard wee are now more ready to plunder God himselfe, and to dispossesse him of what he hath already; then wee would be of promoting the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Churches, if so good a work had beene reserved for these our dayes. But we come to consider the second sort of men, and those are,</p>
            <p>Prophaners, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and Destroyers: we put them together; in regard, like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> they are brethren in iniquity, professed enemies to the house of God. These are the <hi>Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> of Religion, walking with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary steps to all former practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of true devotion and piety. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was so highly affected with an holy zeal to the house of God,
<note place="margin">Ps. 69.71.</note> that it did even eat him up: but these have a zeale that eateth up Gods house. In <hi>Solomons</hi> time it was a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170261:20"/>glory to men to be excellent artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers for the adorning of Gods house;
<note place="margin">Psal. 74.5.</note> but these break downthe carved work thereof of with axes, and hammers. Our Saviour scourged, &amp; ejected the money changers out of the temple, but these are ready to change the temple it selfe into money.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fetrara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roh. up.</hi> 13. <hi>sine tit.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Quàm di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versi mores, quàm adversa aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium, et evertentium mens?</hi> How diverse are the manners of men, and how contrary a mind is there, in the builders, and destroyers, of Gods house?</p>
            <p>But perhaps it may seem to some a very strange thing, that Gods house should come to be destroyed: Is God unable to preserve his owne dwelling from violence, and ruine? Hath the parable any place here,
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.22.</note> that a stronger then hee commeth, and forcibly entereth his habitation? God forbid that any should think so: But let God have the glory of his justice, and man the shame of his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity, by Gods being unwilling to defend his owne house, but rather suffering wicked men to enter, and spoyle his dwelling place, the sinnes of the people provoking God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170261:21"/>unto, and making themselves unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the coutinuance of so great a blessing. It was for the sinne of <hi>Eli,</hi> and his wicked sonnes, that he was threatened with the sight of an enimy in Gods habitation. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.32. God himselfe also made a premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory declaration unto <hi>Solomon,</hi> that when he had cast out of his sight the house which was hallowed to his name, and if the passers by should ask wherefore God had done so, it should be answered, because they had forsaken the Lord their God. 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 9.8.9 10. It was againe thereatned in the dayes of <hi>Iosiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 23.27. that God would cast off the house, of which he had said, His name should be there. And by the prophet <hi>Jeremie,</hi> that God would doe to his temple at Jerusalem, as he he had done to his tabernacle in <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Eli: Ier.</hi> 7.12, 13, 14. and. 26 6. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> also was a trumpet to denounce the same threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.20, 21, 22. To which we will adde the prophet <hi>Hoshea,</hi> by whom, <hi>Chap</hi> 8.1. God also fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned his people that the enimie should come as an eagle against his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170261:21"/>house; swiftly, and greedily to prey upon it. And when these premoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were come to passe, the people themselves confessed the only cause thereof to be their sinnes against God. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 5 12. All which testimonies may assure us, that God, for his part, would have been willing and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in securing his dwelling place from rapine and violence, but being provoked by sinne, he withdrew his mercifull protection, and gave it up to the spoil.</p>
            <p>Neither doth God himself suffer any detriment, or losse hereby, he is not the poorer for his enemies plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of his house: for as he is not enriched by having an earthly habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation furnished with good things, so he is not empoverished though all be taken away: but men who lately were happy, (if they could have seen it) in the fruition of Gods house, &amp; liberty to serve him there, are now bereaved of that which was, and might still have been their greatest comfort, and glory. So that the losse wholly lights upon men, if God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane his Sanctuary,
<note place="margin">Eze. 24.21.</note> the excellency of their strength, the desire of their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170261:22"/>eyes, &amp; that which their soul pitieth. And now their joy being extinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this showre of Divine indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation fallen upon the Sanctuary, the unhappy sonnes of men may lament their own miserie with formerly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed <hi>Israel. Lam.</hi> 2.7. The Lord hath abhorred his Sanctuary, he hath given up into the hand of the enemie the walls of her palaces, they have made a noise in the house of the Lord, as in the day of a solemme feast: And againe. <hi>Isa</hi> 64.11. Our holy, and our beautifull house where our fathers praised thee, is burnt up with fire. When God suffereth it thus farre, <hi>melius carendo, quàm fruendo,</hi> men come to know the comfort, &amp; excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Gods house, better by wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, then by former enjoyments: their eyes may be open when the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved object is taken away. But what for the profaners, and destroyers of Gods house? must they blesse them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in this great impietie with a happy fruition of what they have done to Gods habitation! Let them see to that: their doom is sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in heaven: If they be but abettors approving, and secretly rejoycing at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170261:22"/>what others have done,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 25.3</note> though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps themselves might act nothing in it, yet with the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> for cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Aha, against Gods Sanctuary, when it was profaned, they may be punished for it. And for such as are actors, the justice of God will at one time, or other, find them out, and sue them for those dilapidations. God, when he entereth into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will make the cause of his house, his own; Although his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies rage be against the stones,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Athanas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.</hi> 2. <hi>mihi. pag.</hi> 263. <hi>D.</hi>
               </note> and timber, <hi>Perinde tamen puniri, ac si contra Deum ipsum audacter se effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant:</hi> yet they shall be punished, as if they had audaciously opposed themselves against God himself.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pierius. Hierogl. l.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> Some write of <hi>Diana,</hi> that she was much incensed against <hi>Menalippus,</hi> and <hi>Camethus</hi> for violating her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: If any such thing were done to that fictitious goddesse, she could not revenge her own cause; but the punishment of those men must come from some other hand. But we are sure, and are confirmed by concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent testimonies in severall ages, and places, that the true God will not suffer the violaters of his temple to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170261:23"/>goe unpunished.
<note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> Ask <hi>Belshazzar,</hi> if his abusing the holy vessels of Gods temple,
<note place="margin">2 Cn. 22.1.24.7.</note> did not procure the hand to write bitter things against him. Ask the sonnes of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> if they pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with their plundred holy goods.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioseph Ant. l.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> Ask <hi>Crassus</hi> what he thought of pillaging the temple at Jerusalem, when he went to warre against the <hi>Parthians,</hi> and he can say no lesse, then, that the overthrow of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie was the effect of that sacrilege. Aske <hi>Antiochus,</hi> of whom it was prophesied. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.11. that he should take away the daily sacrifice, and cast down the place of the Sanctuary, which he did, how be thrived with the spoiles, and profanation of God house, and he will referre you to his own confession. 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 6.12, 13. &amp; 2 <hi>Mac.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Niceph. l.</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> 9. Ask the <hi>Vandals,</hi> who, when they warred in Africk, and brought horses into the Christians Churches,
<note place="margin">Theodoret.</note> and were within a little time utterly over thrown by the Moores,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Niceph. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note> if the profanation of those holy plaees was not the most proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cause of their ruine. Ask <hi>Iulian,</hi> who pissing against a Christian Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and was presently smitten with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170261:23"/>a sore disease in his secret parts, whereof he died,
<note place="margin">See S. <hi>Hen. Spelmam de non tem. Eccl. And the preface by his son. M. Clem. Spelm.</hi>
               </note> if he was not puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in his kind. Ask many sad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents of persons, and families recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our own <hi>Chronicles,</hi> if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molishing, spoiling, and profaning of Churches, have not brought many heavie judgments upon the actors, and their posterity, to root them out from the face of the earth. And if notwithstanding these clouds of witnesses, mens stomacks will still be hungry as to long after Churches and Church goods, Ask but the <hi>Apostle,</hi> and he will say; <hi>If any man defile the temple of God, him will God destroy.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. And this in as high in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation (if not higher) as he puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth other sinnes: for it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of our observation, that our Saviour Christ did never manifest his anger in so high a degree, as when he saw the Temple profaned by those that sold oxen, and sheep, and doves,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.15.</note> and the money changers; for then he made a scourge of small cords, and with it, he draw them out of the temple: By which act of his, if we will not learne to take heed of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning Gods house, we may feare the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170261:24"/>execution of <hi>Rehoboams</hi> threatning, in stead of a whip to be chastised with scorpions: If any credence may be given to Mr. <hi>Bucer,</hi> who sadly complaines of that which we account a light thing;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note>
               <hi>Quàm horrendam illi faciunt Divinae Majestati contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, qui templa Domini habent pro deambulacris locisque tam profanis, ut in illis, quaevis impura, &amp; profana cum similibussuis garriunt, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractent. Haec certè tanta est Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni numinis contemptio, ut ea, vel sola pridem meriti sumus omninòde terra exterminari, &amp; suppliciis gravissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis mulctari.</hi> What an horrid des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pight doe they offer to the Divine Majesty, who make Gods Temple their walking places, and use him so profanely, as that they discourse, and handle impure, and profane matters therein, with such as are like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. This surely is so great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Divine Majesty, as that for it alone we have deserved to bee banished from our country, and to be punished with most grievous punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The third sort of men are the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and Restorers of Gods house,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170261:24"/>wherein he that labours (let me bee bold to say) may be accounted Gods benefactor,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 24.16.</note> and have <hi>Jehoiada's</hi> commendation applied to him, that he doth good, both towards God, and towards his house. When the house of God hath lien desolate, or is runne to ruine, and decay, the hearts of such as fear God, and bear good will to his service, is much affected with sorrow, and it pitieth them to see Gods house lie in the dust: Then doe they, with <hi>Daniel</hi> pray,
<note place="margin">Psal. 102.14. Dan. 9.17</note> that God would make his face to shine upon his Sanctuary, that it may be restored to its antient use, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And then will God have mercy upon his dwelling place, either by preserving it from utter desolation, or by granting unto it a gracious resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. But this is to be effected by the devout liberality of men: and God doth therefore worke a time, and opportunity for this holy busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which men may not neglect without further displeasing of God, and provocation of his further wrath. That of <hi>Salomon, Eccles.</hi> 10.18. may be as properly applyed to this as any other sense: Through idlenesse of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170261:25"/>hands the house droppeth through: It being a dangerous idlenesse that suffereth the house of God to be full of holes, chinks, and cranies, through which the wrath of God may distill, and drop upon their heads.
<note place="margin">Ezr. 7.23</note> And why should there be wrath? &amp;c. So that the only way to prevent this evil, is to repair those ruines.</p>
            <p>It was laid to the charge of the Citty of <hi>Rome</hi> by one of their own Poets that their slacknesse in repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ruined Temples, was the cause of their calamities.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Delicta majorum immeritus lues
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Horat. Od.</hi> 6. <hi>lib.</hi> 3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Romane; donec templa refeceris</l>
               <l>Aedesque labentes deorum, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And the same is charged upon Gods people by a divine Prophet, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.9. Ye looked for much, and lo, it came to little, and when yee brought it home, I did blow upon it, And why? saith the Lord of hosts, Because of my house that is wast &amp;c. Justly might the land be desolate, when Gods house, through the slouthfulnesse of men, lay desolate: Justly might God cause the earth to withold her fruits, when the hearts, and hands of men withhold the fruits
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170261:25"/>of their pious liberality for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of Gods dwelling place:
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> for those that honour God, God will honour, and those that are free-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towards God, shall find God so towards them againe. So that there is no better way of stirring up Gods beneficence, then by contributing (or rather retributing) of our substance to the house of God.
<note place="margin">Luk. 7.5.</note> The Jewes mooving our Saviour in the behalfe of the Centurion, used this argument, He hath built us a synagogue: which argument surely hath not lost its force in the sight of God, in behalf of any that shall raise God a dwelling place, or restore the breaches thereof. If therefore we desire that God should be liberall to us, it is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that we incite, and nourish Gods liberality with our own: If we desire to receive from the good hand of God, blessings, either corporall, or spirituall, 'tis a good way to respect the house where they are to be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that, as is said <hi>Isay.</hi> 65.8. of the cluster, Destroy it not, for a blessing is in it, may we say of the house of God, Destroy it not, suffer it not to goe to ruine, or decay, for there are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170261:26"/>blessings in it, and it is the only place, which we, and all that we have doe fare the better for: For, if God blessed the house of <hi>Obed Edom</hi> for the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Arke there,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.11.</note> why may not Gods house be a cause of blessing to that people amongst whom it is built?
<note place="margin">Iudg. 17.13.</note> Or, if <hi>Micah</hi> concluded from the proper person officiating in God ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Now will the Lord doe me good, seeing I have a <hi>Levite</hi> to my priest: Why may not the people of God assure themselves of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse towards them, when they have a peculiar and proper place for God to dwell among them, and where they may meet with God to desire such blessings as God will give in that place?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beru. mihi Col.</hi> 413. <hi>D</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Mons iste mons uber, bonorum omnium cumulus, mons voluptatis aeternae domus Dei est:</hi> that moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is a fruitfull mountaine, a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surie of all good things, a mountaine of eternall pleasure is the house of God. And whosoever loveth it shall inherit that promise. <hi>Psal.</hi> 65.4. to be satisfied with the goodnesse of Gods house, even of his holy temple. If then we shall rightly consider the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold necessities which daily lie upon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170261:26"/>us, those on our part towards God, that we duly serve and worship him; and those on Gods part towards us, that he daily preserve and blesse us, we shall easily see a necessity of Gods house. And such a necessity,
<note place="margin">Luk. 10.43.</note> that, as our Saviour said to Martha, One thing is necessary, may we say of the house of God, One place is nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssary: there being no such necessity of any place, or building whatsoever, as there is of an house for God: And it were better that we should have no houses for our selves to dwell in, then that God should want an habitation wherein to reside amongst us, and wherein (as once the tabernacle ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for that use. <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.43.) we may meet with God, to converse with him, and to exchange, <hi>officia pro beneficiis,</hi> our services for his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings. This, because we shall have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to resume, ere we end our dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, we shal here finish our first con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, The necessity of Gods house.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be examined, is, The Dignity of Gods house, Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which there is no small contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie, or agitation amongst men: For as we read, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.9. the daughters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170261:27"/>asked this question concerning Christ, the Churches beloved, What is thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved more then another beloved? So many ask concerning Gods house, What is it more then another place? And which is more to be wondred at, this question is not only discussed betwixt Christians and the generall rabble of heathen men (for even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst heathens some have been found so devout in their way, that they have had a reverend esteem of the houses of their own gods) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Christians on both sides is this matter debated, and by the one part resolved for the negative:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Salvian. de guber. lib.</hi> 3.</note> which is no new, but an old error, there having been such many yeeres agoe, <hi>Qui ecclesias minoris reverentiae habent, quàm cujuslibet minimi, ac munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palis judicis domum,</hi> who had Churches in lesse reverence, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem, then the house of an inferiour judge, or magistrate. And which is yet more to be wondred at, the men of our times that oppose the dignity of Churches are not of the lewd, and more debauched sort of people; but men professing religion, and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and would be thought the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170261:27"/>only religious people in the world: These contend amain for Gods Time and nothing at all for his Place: but against it: Crying up the Sabbath (which in Gods name let them doe) but crying down the Temple:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In hoc major of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensa est, quod portem sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae pro commodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nosto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate deligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, partem pro Dei injuria praeterimus. Salvian. l.</hi> 3. <hi>mihi. p.</hi> 77. Mal. 1.10.</note> When it is not lawfull to separate those whom God hath joyned, 'tis done, not considering the offence of muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating Scripture, which commandeth that due reverence be given to both, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.2. ye shal keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary. And which may stretch our admiration further still, amongst these men which oppose the Dignity of Churches, are found priests &amp; ministers, who are the proper officers to serve in these places, and by which they have their meanes of livelyhood: Serving at the altar, and living by the altar, and to debase the altar! not opening nor shutting the doores of Gods house for naught, and yet to open them so for nought, as to let in naughtinesse, profanesse, and parity with other common pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Let the world judge how conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous this offence is in them above Christians of the ordinary, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sort. And surely this very thing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170261:28"/>deserves a serious disquisition, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, amongst the many errours of us priests, and ministers, which have brought the late pressures more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily upon us, then any other persons, or calling whatsoever, this may not goe for one, the contempt of Gods house: some by their perversnesse de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>basing it, others by their supinenesse nor defending it, if this amongst our other defaults to God, hath not caus'd him to debase us, and denuding us of patronage, and protection, hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed us to the wills of them that hate us.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.17.</note> And no marvell, if we hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made the table, and house of God contemptible, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.7. shall be made by God contemptible also, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.9. If we shall so demean our selves, as, with the sonnes of <hi>Eli,</hi> to make men abhorre the offering of the Lord, and to despise the service of God in his house, which besides other wayes, is done by undervaluing the house, it is but just with God to make men abhorre, and despise us: If we kindle a fire to consume the glory of the temple, the fire of Gods displeasure doth justly consume our glory.</p>
            <p>But what is it concerning Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170261:28"/>that is thus impugned? 'Tis their sanctity and holinesse: for, as God once complained. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. They put no difference betwixt the holy, and profane: So may he doe now, there being no discrimination ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged betwixt the houses of God, and our own houses. Many there are, who, though they coldly assent to the Necessity of Churches, yet they hotly oppose their holinesse. And yet this is a thing which devout heathens have not denyed to the temples of their idol gods,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. de nat. deorum. l.</hi> 1</note> as the Romane Oratour pleades for them, and reprooves the profaner sort, who were contrary minded, <hi>Non Egyptij, non Syri, uec ferè cuncta Barbaries: firmiores enim videas opiniones de bestijs quibusdam, quàm apud nos de sanctissimis templis:</hi> Not the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, nor Syrians, nor all the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous nations would do so: for we may see amongst them more rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end opinions of some certaine beasts, than there are amongst us, of our most holy temples. I would this could not be charged upon us Christians.</p>
            <p>And upon this ground could not those heathens endure that their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170261:29"/>should be profaned, or polluted.
<q>Pueri sacer est locus,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pers. Sat.</hi> 1</note>
                  <hi>extrà</hi>
               </q>
               <hi>Meiete.</hi> Boyes, the place is holy, therefore pisse without, said an antient Poet. And of lat one of our own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men being a prisoner in <hi>Sally</hi> was scourged for this default:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames Wadsworth in his Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim. p.</hi> 41.</note> for as he returned from the fountaine with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and chancing to make his own water against the Church wall, a Moore seeing him, presently made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and asked him, whether it was the custome of his Countrey so to doe, if it was, it was not the custome of theirs, and thereupon beat him, till he left him half dead. But this, which Saracens and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Moores, out of a venerable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to their Churches have abstain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from, is too commonly committed amongst us Christians, who boast that we only have the knowledge of the true God amongst us; and though to his Name, and service alone these sacred buildings are erected, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, yet are they unworthily profaned, vilified, and branded with ignominious speeches, defamations, nicknames, and the defenders of their holinesse charged with Superstition.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170261:29"/>
            <p>But if it were soberly considered, that the contempt of Gods house reflects upon God himselfe, it would surely then be of better fame, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation: for, if under the law the saying, that the table of the Lord was contemptible, was a polluting of Gods name. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.12. why should not Christians think that the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach of Gods house under the Gospel, is so to? And if it was once accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted blasphemie to speak against the temple. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.13. why should it not still be so accounted?</p>
            <p>And verily it was so (or little lesse then so) accounted, when in the Councell of Gangra above thirteen hundred yeeres agoe, a Canon was enacted, If any man shall say the house of God is contemptible, &amp;c. Let him be accursed. St. <hi>Paul</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before Festus, acquitted himselfe from saying any thing against the Temple. <hi>Act.</hi> 25.8. And how the revilers of Christian temples will answer it to God, Let them see to it.</p>
            <p>The spirits of contradiction now raigning in the world, and like frogs come out of the mouth of the dragon, and of the beast, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.13. are ten
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170261:30"/>croaking against the holinesse of our Christian temples, have hereby got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten great advantages against the Gospell: for First, they have distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the peace of the Church, kindl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a fire of dissention within her bowels. 2. They have caused schismes in the Church, withdrawing many from the Communion of saints in the publick, and appointed place. 3. They keep infidels, and heathens from the Church, making them to despise our Christian religion, because we despise our Churches. 4. It hath opened a doore to Sacrilege, that the abomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of desolation may enter, and stand in the holy place: for, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>basing of Gods house, in saying, that it is no better then other houses shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth the stomacks of covetous men to hunger after it, and wideneth their throats to swallow the materialls, and appurtunances thereof, with as little reluctancy, and regret of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, as if they had pulled down but one of their own houses. And these spirits are now much manifested in the world: for it appears by cleer te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies in severall places, that the premisses of their arguments against
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170261:30"/>Gods house, conclude with self-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, and desire of the things there to their own use; goodly stones, and tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ready squared will serve to build houses for themselves, and there are few that embrace the premisses, that Gods house is not holy, but they are ready to put the conclusion also in practice, therefore, why may it not be pulled down? If God himself lay at the mercy of these men, they would soon take his earthly habitation from him, and the opinion of Gods house not being holy, will beget an opinion of their own innocency in so doing. It was once a sad complaint against the house of Judah. <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.9. that Gods heritage was unto him, as a speckled bird, or as <hi>Junius</hi> reades it <hi>Digitata,</hi> a bird with fingers, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons. griping and raking from God all they could: I wish it were not so with us.</p>
            <p>But let us hear what can be said a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the holinesse of Churches: for we will doe the adversary that right which <hi>Felix</hi> did to S. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 26 1. in permitting him to speak for himself: where we shall produce only such arguments as have most colour,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170261:31"/>and show of reason, which are these three.</p>
            <p>The first objection against the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Christian temples is taken from the consideration of Salomons temple in Jerusalem. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>1</label> This, as once it was a place of defence, being a strong cittadell in that city, (for it held out stoutly against the Romans when all the citie besides was taken) so is it now made a place of offence, to beat downe the holinesse of Gods houses under the Gospell, that they should not be partners with it in holinesse. The holinesse of that temple is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable, and no man of reason will dare to dispute against it, in regard the Scriptures doe in many places call it holy: but against the holiness of our Christian temples, it is argued, That the temple of Jerusalem was typicall, and so to cease, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, and with it, the holinesse thereof, so that there remaineth no more holinesse in Churches under the Gospel.</p>
            <p>As concerning the typicall nature of that Temple, wee will not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deny, that, that temple might be a type of Christ, or of his Church
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170261:31"/>under the Gospell,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wil. Guild</hi> in his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> unvai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>p.</hi> 175.</note> although it will not be hard to proove it by just parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, yet to demonstrate which only are so, and no lesse, will not be easie: for although many things might be alledged as carrying decent conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, and resemblances, yet whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were therefore types, is still doubtfull, and requires a cleerer evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, then bare saying. It is not to be denied that the services, and sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the temple were most of them typicall, and figurative; but as to the fabrick of the temple it self, and the holinesse thereof, we cannot assent that these were so typicall, as to have their period at Christ, but conceive there is reason enough to make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve they were morall, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue under the Gospell, as we shall shew anon.</p>
            <p>And as for the destruction of the temple, it was not to come to passe by vertue of the ceremoniall law, as if any precept obliged the Iewes to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake or ruinate the temple, as, at Christ they were to lay aside their legall ceremonies, and sacrifices; only it was to be abolished as to the present use, so that those ceremoniall rites,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170261:32"/>and services were no longer to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, nor those kinds of sacrifices to be offered therein, when Christ, the substance of them all, was come, and had offered himselfe: but yet that temple was to be destroyed (as liable to destruction, which afterwards sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon it) by the justice of God: Not to cease then, and utterly to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished by Christ, but at him and by him to receive a kind of regeneration (as we may so say) and thenceforth to serve, and continue to a new use, to wit an Evangelical; that now, new, and spiritual sacrifices should be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therein unto God, whose house it was still to continue: the beesome which swept away the ceremoniall law, having no power to abolish Gods name called thereon, nor Gods propriety therein, nor that service unto which it was now to be transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>For first; Seeing it was prophesied, <hi>Isa.</hi> 56 7. Mine house (still it was Gods house) shall be called an house of prayer for all people: for the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles as well as the Jewes; what like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood was there, that it should be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished when the Gentiles were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170261:32"/>and called? What entrance, or admission could therebe for them into an abolished temple? Would God prepare them a place, and call them to it, and when they were converted, take it away that they should not find it?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Our Saviour himselfe saith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. That he came not to destroy the law, but to fulfill it: He came not then to destroy the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but to terminate and fulfil, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ceremoniall use thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He saith again, <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.14. When ye shall see the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of desolation standing where it ought not. Therefore the fabrick of the temple should not have been made desolate, nor beene destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If it should have been destroyed, it would most probably have been so at Christs death, and then have received its doom in some eminent and extraordinary way, as God the owner thereof should have pleased: but all the violence it suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered at the death of Christ, was the renting of the Vail, signifying Christs entrance into the Holy of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170261:33"/>holies; but as for the temple it self, that stood, and continued firm in all the parts thereof, to serve for further use under the Gospel.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Legall persons were not destroyed, to wit, the priests, but they ceased as to their leviticall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and ministrations, and were capable of being translated into the Evangelicall priesthood, if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour should have thought fit to call any of them thereunto; as some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ancients say, that <hi>James</hi> the brother of our Lord was of the Priests race:
<note place="margin">Epiphan. haer.</note> and afterwards <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> a <hi>Levite</hi> was called, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.36. &amp; 13, 2. If then legal Persons were not destroyed, Why should the place?</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Temple was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed; but, as we have said, not from any terminative necessity of the ceremonial law, but by the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of God, inflicting his wrath upon his rebellious people. And this was done forty years after our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours passion (God forbearing them so long as he did their forefathers in the wilderness) by the wicked Jews themselves,
<note place="margin">Psal. 95.</note> opposing the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170261:33"/>Government, and making the Temple their last refuge and sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de pec. mer. cap.</hi> 4.</note> the <hi>Romans</hi> also helping for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the destruction thereof. So that, as St. <hi>Austin</hi> disputeth against the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> that, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not sinned, he should not have dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, out of any necessity of nature but would have continued immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; so may we say of the Temple, If the Jews had not sinned, if they would have received Christ as their Messias, and Saviour, walking ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his new, and Evangelical way, and their children after them in the same manner; they might have been possessed of their city Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, and the temple therein might have flourished, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an house of prayer, to this very day. But as hath been said before, God gave up his house to the spoile for the sins of his people; so did he now, for the iniquity of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And although the high Priests, and Rulers, with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the common Jews, filled up the measure of their Fathers, and outwent them in iniquity by cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Lord of glory; yet, as God,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170261:34"/>before he destroyed Jerusalem by the Chaldeans,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.15.</note> having compassion on his people, and on his dwelling place, sent his Prophets unto them summoning them to repent, which had they done, neither their city, nor temple had beene destroyed; so did he to this generation, call them by his own son, and he by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, to repentance; the accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof might have preserved their city, and temple from destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither would that Temple, so continuing, have been devested of its holiness, that it should have remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned naked, and bare, at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Christ, by whom things were to be made, rather better, then worse; for it would have seemed a strange thing, that the Temple should, at Christ's comming, have degenerated, from an holy, into a prophane or common place, and be degraded to a parity with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dwelling houses, which, before the comming of Christ, it was farre from. The Temple, for its part, might have wished, that Christ should rather not have come at all,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170261:34"/>then to come to its detriment, and loss.</p>
            <p>That therefore which a mind, so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly devout, may admit, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, is, that holiness, during the law, was limitted, and confined to the temple at Jerusalem, but by the comming of Christ, it became dilated, and diffused to all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Temples wheresoever they were to be erected throughout the world, to the name of God, and his service. And to this we may apply that of our Saviour to the woman of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, Ioh</hi> 4.21. The hour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth when ye shall neither in this mountaine, nor yet at Jerusalem, worship the Father:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Superstitio Superstes. pag.</hi> 7.</note> Not that these words should lay all places levell in regard of holinesse, to which they look not, as not in the letter, so not in the sense, but rather import a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty drawing neer of worshipping God in Christian Temples all the world over: As if our Saviour had said, Ye <hi>Samaritans</hi> confine your worshippers to this your own tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Jewes theirs, to their temple at Jerusalem; but it will not be long ere the servants of God shall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170261:35"/>be freed from these engagements, and have Temples in their owne countries, where they may offer up such spirituall sacrifices as shall be proper, and agreeable to Gods reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, refined to a higher perfection. And this liberty would procure great ease and facility to the people of God, in his service and worship; that, whereas under the law, the Jews were bound to repair at certain times of the year unto Jerusalem, from their severall countries into which they were dispersed, as may appear, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.5. Now, by the comming of Christ, they should be free, serving God at home, with less labour and expence, having Temples of their owne wherein to perform divine offices. So that those words of our Saviour seem to have so little relation to the period of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness in Jerusalems Temple, as that rather on the contrary, they may be thought to insinuate a participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of holiness (though perhaps not caused in all equall respects) in our Christian Churches with that temple at Jerusalem.</p>
            <p>A second Objection against the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170261:35"/>holinesse of Churches, is, the silence of the Scriptures, especially of the new Testament wherein (as it is said) there is nothing to prove that our present Christian Churches are holy. Whether this be true, that nothing is to be found in the new Testament to prove our Churches holy, neither directly, nor by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence we shall examine anon, when we shall make our answer an argument on this behalf.</p>
            <p>But some object, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> That our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were built by Papists. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is objected by some of the more ignorant sort, who think our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to consist in so direct an opposition to Popery, as that what ever the Papists do, must be disal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, &amp; the contrary done, for fear of being popishly affected; (a su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious fear which too meny are infected now adayes) but none of any reasonable learning dare object it. And this argument fights not so much against the holinesse, as the very essence, and use of many of our late built Churches. If the original of Churches in this nation was exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170261:36"/>no doubt, but some would be found to have been built by the ancient Britains, before ever the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> executed (or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to execute) any authority here, which was not till <hi>Austin</hi> the Monk was sent hither by <hi>Gregory</hi> the first, who when he came (not to plant, but rather to restore the Christian religion) he found many Churches already built, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self might be a meanes of adding more to the number. But afterwards upon the multiplication of inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and the growth of religion, the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and <hi>Danes</hi> having suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively subdued this kingdome, these two nations were both of them great Church-builders, the <hi>Danes</hi> building their Churches with blunt steeples, and the <hi>Saxons</hi> with spires: Now if any will question the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of these people in those dayes, it may be easily shewed, that upon their couversion to the Christian faith which they received here in <hi>England,</hi> they were not in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall respects subject to the <hi>Roman</hi> Sea, so, as is claimed in these our dayes; and besides that, the Romish
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170261:36"/>religion was not then by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees so corrupt, as now it is. After the comming in of the <hi>Normans,</hi> the number of Churches still increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, whose particular founders must be clearly convicted of Popery, else the argument is not good against the Churches which they built. But many Churches in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom have clearly had Protestant founders, having been built by pious and devout men, since our late ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting off the Romish usurped supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and since our reformation from their errors: so that the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment strikes not, at all our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; but those before Popery, and those since Popery, must be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if the Objectors will be honest, and do them right, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all for the supposed faultiness of some, especially seeing the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors are not able to separate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the sheep and the goats, to shew particularly which Churches are liable to their exception.</p>
            <p>And yet, as to the Objection, if it should be granted, that all, or some of our Churches have been built by as corrupted Papists as ever
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170261:37"/>were, yet this hindreth them not from being employed to the worship and service of God, in a way more pure, and more agreeable to Gods word and will, then that of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists is.</p>
            <p>In the primitive times of the Church, honest, and good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans made no scruple of converting heathen Temples to the service of the true God: neither their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, nor their former Use were thought sufficient crimes against them, if conveniency and necessity required that they should be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed a better way. Many Jewish Synagogues were not so abrogated with the law, but that they were translated into Christian Churches,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mihi to m.</hi> 2 <hi>pag.</hi> 19.</note> as <hi>Athanasius</hi> writeth, &amp; is evident by the like examples in our owne nation. And for idolatrous Temples of the heathen, their translation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Christian Temples is evident e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by variety of testimonies, wherein S. <hi>Austin</hi> is as clear as can be desired, <hi>Alia falsorum numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num templa dirui, alia in meliorem usum commutari consuevêre.</hi> They appointed some of the temples of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170261:37"/>the idol gods to be destroyed; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be converted to a better use. And in his 50 Epistle to <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licola,</hi> he testifieth the translation of such buildings from an heathenish to a Christian use. Again, in his 154 Epistle to <hi>Bonifacius,</hi> speaking of this kind of translating of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, he compareth it to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of men, <hi>Hoc de illis fit, quod de ipsis hominibus; cum ex sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegis &amp; impiis in veram religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mutantur.</hi> It is with them, as it is with men, which being sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious and wicked,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bosius de Cruce. pag.</hi> 481.</note> they are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the true religion. <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an Aegyptian <hi>Mithrium,</hi> or Temple, into a Christian Church.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eips. de mag. Ʋrbis Rom. pag.</hi> 128.</note>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the fourth of that name, Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> obtained of the Emperour <hi>Phocas,</hi> that he might make a Christian Temple of the <hi>Pantheon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">W. Tho. <hi>Hist. Ital. fol.</hi> 189.</note> which had been erected to the honour of all the gods. The Temple of <hi>Hercules</hi> in Millain, was also translated in like manner. And if the records of our own nation do not deceive us,
<note place="margin">Florus Hist.</note>
               <hi>Lucius</hi> the first Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian King of this land, converted
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170261:38"/>all the idolatrous Temples to a Christian use, and placed over them three Archbishops, and eight and twenty Bishops. Afterwards when <hi>Austin</hi> came into this land to repair the decay of Christianity. <hi>Gregory</hi> the first, then Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to <hi>Melitus</hi> an Abbot, that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi> should destroy the Idols of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but suffer their Temples to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 71. <hi>lib.</hi> 9.</note> giving this reason for it, <hi>Nam gens illa verum Deum cognoscens, ad loca quae consuevit, familiariùs occurrit.</hi> The nation being brought to the knowledge of the true God, willl come more familiarly to those places to which they were accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Then let our Churches be built by whomsoever,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pol. Synt. Col.</hi> 646. 2. <hi>D. Zep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perus de leg. forens. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> and to what use soever, <hi>Possunt à Christianis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgata converti,</hi> they may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by Christians, and converted to the service of God. <hi>Templa etiam si in abusum conversa sub Papatu fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt, solus tamen illorum abusus corrigi debet.</hi> Although Churches under the Papacy were abused, yet the abuse only ought to be correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And blessed be God, we have seen our English Churches (if built
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170261:38"/>by Papists) purged from the dregs and pollutions of Popish services, with which in former ages they were most miserably defiled. And if, as I have said, it should be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that our Churches had such Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish founders, we might then look upon it as a mercy from God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the reformed religion, that as once he brought his people Israel to houses which themselves builded not, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.11. So hath he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for us, that our Churches should be built to our hand, and cost us nothing: foreseeing the coldness of these last dayes, that if the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Churches had been deferred untill now, they would scarce have ever been built, many hands would have shrunck from so generall a work, as is now established amongst us; especially they who declaime against our Churches, and decline them, as being built by Papists; they, of all others, would have been most backward to set them up.</p>
            <p>In these arguments lyeth all the strength of that opposition which is now made against the holiness, and use of our Christian Churches,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170261:39"/>and we hope they have received a reasonable satissaction. Our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour must now address it self to the affirmative part, to examine what may be said in defence of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, if possibly to settle the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof in the minds of sober Christians, that there may be no scruple, nor further disputes about it.</p>
            <p>Where, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> in the first place, an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in defence of this holiness may be drawn from the name, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of sacriledge. The Greeks call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the Latine, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegium,</hi> which is nothing else but a taking away of any thing that is Sacred, or Holy: And such things only are those that be dedicated to God, and his service, the taking away whereof is sacriledge; Now such a sinne there is under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. therefore there are such things under the Gospel. And if Lands, Money, Chalices, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther materialls dedicated to Gods house and service be holy: What should hinder the House it self from being holy?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2d</label> A second argument may be drawn
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170261:39"/>from Gods propriety in these our Churches, which are built and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to his name. God hath a two-fold propriety in the things of this world. First, a generall or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal propriety, <hi>Domini est terra,</hi> The earth is the Lords, and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness thereof, <hi>Psal.</hi> 24.1. Secondly, a special or peculiar propriety, which is either by Gods owne election, when he chooseth and designeth any thing for himself; or, by the gift of men, when men express their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and devout thankfulness unto God, by giving him a portion of such good things as they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him: And, what is thus given to God, becomes his by a more peculiar and speciall interess then it was before. For, as God, though he might justly challenge all the cattel upon a thousand hills for his own, <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.10. yet such a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them as were the male first<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or by the owners free will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed for sacrifices, these were Gods more then the rest, So likewise o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things being made Gods this secondary way, he hath in them a double interest and propriety. And
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170261:40"/>this may yet more fully appeare in that of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29, 14. <hi>Of thine owne have we given thee:</hi> first it was Gods own by way of universall right, and he gave it to <hi>David,</hi> then <hi>David</hi> gave it again to God; whereby that which was so given, became Gods after another manner then it was before.</p>
            <p>And this speciall propriety which God hath in things, is that which altereth the nature of the things themselves (as now of Gods pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session) and maketh them to become holy, which, whilst they were Gods, by generall propriety onely, they were not.</p>
            <p>The things then, which either God himselfe made choice of for his, did thereby become holy, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Josh.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.23; Or which the devotion of men conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to God, as the Vessels of the Temple for which there was no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press command, became holy also, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 8.28. So likewise did a house or a field, the consecration whereof was onely voluntary on mans part, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.14, 16, 21, 28. As also the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> for so long
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170261:40"/>time as their vow lasted, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.8. And this shewes a plain difference (necessary to be taken notice of) betwixt God and man, in relation to the possession of things: that God is another manner of Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary then man can be making those things which are his, by this pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar right to be holy, which the possession of men cannot do: for, flocks and heards, gold and silver,, are not holy whilst they are mans, but if once they become Gods, they are thenceforth holy: The stateliest palace of the greatest earthly king, is not holy although it hath so roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and magnificent an owner; but if once an house be built, and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God, and his service, it is holy, from Gods propriety therein. As it is with times: of those dayes which are in themselves common, if any day be set apart by the people of God, for thanksgiving, or humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, that separation to such an holy use, sanctifieth the day, and maketh it holy: <hi>Sanctifie a fast, Ioel.</hi> 2.15. So it is with places, the house which is set apart for Gods service becometh a sanctified and holy place.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170261:41"/>
            <p>This may make very fair towards the satisfying an Objection which is urged by some, who, although they grant the house of God to be holy, yet it is with a limitation, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the service of God there: for God (say they) commeth to meet his people in his house, and Gods presence there, at that time, sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the place; but, the people of God dissolving, and the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion breaking up, they, and God, after a manner part, and so the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness of the place for that time cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth: 'Tis true, that God meeteth his people, when they convene in in his House, thus far we all agree: but if it be observed from <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. that the recording of Gods name upon his House, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thither to meet with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> Yates <hi>in his Ser. pag.</hi> 2.</note> are two distinct things, it may be concluded, that Gods name and propriety are sufficient for the san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying his House, even in those distances of time when there is no celebration of any publick service, the place being still the House of God, dedicated to his name and service, and so retaining that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170261:41"/>whereof we now speak, it is, by virtue of that, set in a capacity of holiness. And is not the sabbath day holy even in those vacant hours, when there are no religious offices performed, either publique or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, but people are employed about necessary affaires, as feeding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves or their cattel or other things which God himself is pleased to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spense with? Why then not the same also with Gods place, in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancies of divine service?</p>
            <p>If it be further demanded, why there should be any such dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under the Gospell, when the scriptures of the new Testament do neither require any such, nor signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Gods acceptation thereof? It may be demanded again, Where do the Scriptures forbid them to be done, or condemn them being done? Under the law, mens hands were tyed behind them, that they might not erect houses for God in any part of the world, save onely the Temple at Jerusalem; but now that law is ceased: If therefore, <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> before there was any law had power to destinate an house for God
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170261:42"/>which he did (though it was but an altar) <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22. Why have not the people of God, after the law, power, to appoint houses for God, in such places as are judged meet and convenient? To Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem we need not, and indeed we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not repair: the Temple there, is not; and the city is in the possession of infidels. Yet if it were not so, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that temple, nor city, nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, would suffice for the whole Church dispersed all the world over: How miserable therefore would the Church be under the Gospel, if it were not necessary and expedient to erect Houses for the service of God elsewhere? Must the whole Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church rue the iniquity of the Jews, as to be deprived of places for Gods worship, because the Jews by their sins brought desolation upon their own temple?</p>
            <p>A third Argument may be drawn from the typical nature of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3d.</label> I mean not, that which was ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, to continue to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Christ, and then to end, but as the Temple may be thought to have respect to the state
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170261:42"/>of glory, and is no other then a type and figure of heaven it selfe, as hath been touched before: for that house is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Templum omne coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li figuram servat. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caetas in Greg. Naz. Orat.</hi> 41.</note> The true taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.2. And this House is the type of that. Now, what manner of place is heaven? Is it not an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place sutable to him that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth therein? And is it not therefore convenient that that holy place should be typified by a place which is holy also? Must not the House of Gods gracious presence have some affinity with that of his glorious presence? Shall not Gods House <hi>in viâ,</hi> come as near as may be to that <hi>in patriâ?</hi> Otherwise, if our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were not holy, there would be no proportion, nor resemblance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the type and the thing, the shadow and the substance, which is not probable. If then the Temple at Jerusalem (as once it was holy) should have so put off its holiness at Christ, as that he being come, it should be such no longer, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently our Christian Temples should not be holy: What a great chasme or distance would there be betwixt the shadow and the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170261:43"/>the typicall and true Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Reason therefore may admit, as apparent enough, that the type should retain its holiness untill the substance comes; and so our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houses of God to be holy unto the worlds end, when grace shall end in glory, and the number of Saints being compleated, the whole Church shall be clothed upon with that house which is from heaven.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Far be it, that we should deny Christ to be the substance of the law, that is of the transient types, figures, and shadows thereof; but this doth not hinder heaven from being the substance of our Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Temples, nor the holiness of that place from inferring the holiness of these.</p>
            <p>A fourth Argument may be drawn from the Authority of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and learned Divines, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> who have not onely called the house of God, holy, but asserted its being so which might (if they did not leane too much to their own wisdom) satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the mindes of other men, and make them acquiesce in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of such eminent lights of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170261:43"/>Church: for we may well think that men so divinely inspired, would not have done so,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Cels. mihi pag.</hi> 535.</note> but out of a full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion that it is so. <hi>Origen</hi> taxeth <hi>Zeno</hi> the Critick, for saying, <hi>Pro sancto non habendum quod strux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint homines,</hi> It is not to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed holy which is built by the hands of men which <hi>Origen</hi> would not have done,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De vit. Const. c.</hi> 1. <hi>De gub. l.</hi> 3 <hi>pag.</hi> 88.</note> if himself had not been of the contrary opinion. <hi>Eusebius</hi> calleth the Churches of his time, <hi>Sacras Aedes,</hi> Holy houses. <hi>Salvia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Sacraria,</hi> Sacred, or holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, St.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mihi Col.</hi> 346. <hi>D.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Bernard</hi> applyeth that of <hi>Psal.</hi> 93.5. <hi>Holiness becommeth thine house for ever:</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose also, <hi>An verò domum Dei quis dubitet samctam esse, de quâ legitur, Domum tuam decet sanctitudo?</hi> Will any doubt (saith he) that the house of God is holy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 39. <hi>apud Theod Bnlsamon.</hi>
               </note> of which it is said, <hi>Holiness becommeth thine house for ever?</hi> The Councill of <hi>Trullo</hi> calls Churches, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, holy places, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Canc. 7. Can. 13. <hi>apud. Bais.</hi>
               </note> Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable houses. Another Councill calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, sacred, devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or holy houses.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170261:44"/>
            <p>WE come now in the fifth and last place to examine, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no, any places may be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of the Scriptures, especially the new Testament, to prove the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness of our Christian Temples. Where; first, that of our Saviour in St. <hi>Matthew, Chap.</hi> 24.15. offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it self: When ye shall see the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations of desolation stand in the <hi>Holy</hi> place: where our Saviour speaketh of the temple at Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, calling it <hi>holy</hi> when the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of desolation seized upon it, which was forty years after his passion, and when the temple was not Jewish, but Christan: If then the temple retained its holiness after Christs death, then consequently our temples may be holy also. If it shall be replyed, that the word <hi>holy</hi> in our Saviours speech, is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of the Temple, at that time when he spake those words, as if he had said, In that place which now is <hi>holy;</hi> for as yet the temple had not parted with its holiness, Christ being not yet offered up: It may be answered, that the word <hi>holy</hi> there, is to extend further then our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170261:44"/>death, to that very time when the Romans came against the city Jerusalem, and the temple in that fatall storm became desolate; as may appear by the words otherwise ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by St. <hi>Mark, Chap.</hi> 13.20. When ye shall see the abomination of desolation, standing <hi>where it ought not:</hi> So that the temple ought not to have been destroyed, neither the Jews, nor the Romans, ought to have done any violence to it, but it ought to have been preserved from violation on both sides, because, as St. <hi>Matthew</hi> hath it, It was the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> place. The next place, is that of the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>The tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God is holy:</hi> where perhaps some will snatch the words, and presently run with them to the next, where the Apostle particularly mentioneth the personall, or spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall temple, the <hi>Corinthians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and affirm this to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church which is holy, but the words assert not any holiness in the locall, or materiall temple: To those that shall say thus, we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, that the Apostle first asserteth a generall truth in a generall propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170261:45"/>Whatsoever is the temple of God, it is holy; and then he apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this generall to a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration in a spiritual sense, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, that as the materiall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is <hi>holy,</hi> by being dedicated to Gods service, even so the spirituall Church in <hi>Corinth,</hi> was, and ought to be, by being redeemed from the world, and giving themselves up to the service of God. So that, grant the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to be an holy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as every other particular Church is, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. yet those words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> are so far from denying the holiness of Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall house, that, by way of allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, or similitude, they strongly confirm it. And so Expositers upon the place, have respect to both sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. <hi>Est quidem in materiall templo quaedam sacramentalis sanctitas:</hi> There is, saith <hi>Aquinas,</hi> a certain sacramental holiness in the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all temple. And with him agree, <hi>Gualterus, Peter Martyr, Estius.</hi> And no doubt many more, if it were necessary to produce a cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, for the strengthening of this argument.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170261:45"/>
            <p>A third place is that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. Christ is not ascended into the <hi>holy</hi> places made with hands. The Originall is onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Holies, without expressing the word, <hi>Places,</hi> which yet is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, as the words following, <hi>made with hands,</hi> will demonstrate, Here then the Apostle maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>holy</hi> places, and what places can they be thought to have been, if they were not temples and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? And although the words may seem to have a primary respect to the temple of Jerusalem,
<note place="margin">Calv. in loc.</note> which was yet standing, <hi>Sanctum pro Sanctuario,</hi> the Holy, being put for the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary: yet is it worthy of our obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that that Temple is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Holy by the Apostle under the Gospel, as still retaining its proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holiness after Christ's death, which it had before. And if there were then any other Temples, or Churehes built elsewhere in that early age of Christianity,
<note place="margin">M. Meade</note> as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of no mean account affirm, this saying of the Apostle may have respect to them also: And had these our Churches present, been erected
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170261:46"/>in those dayes, they might have then more unquestionably come in for their share in that Scripture, which nevertheless they have not lost, by their being like St. <hi>Paul,</hi> born out of due season, erected ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages after the writing of that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle; but, as the temple at Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem was holy under the Gospel, even so are our Churches also: for, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apostles rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. If the first fruits be holy, the lump also is holy; and if the root be holy, so are the branches; the temple of Jerusalem being the first fruits, and the root (as we may say) of all our Christian Temples, ours do certainly participate with that in holiness, as having the same efficient, material, formal, and final cause, to wit, the service and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God: in every Evangelical respect so agreeing are they with it, that it would be strange if they should disagree in this of <hi>holiness.</hi> Neither are there wanting the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of pious and judicious men,
<note place="margin">Sr. H. S. <hi>denon Tem. Eccl. p.</hi> 16.</note> who apply those words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle to this purpose, inferring the holiness of our Churches from the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170261:46"/>holiness of the Temple,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>C. Dow. Disc. of the Sab. p.</hi> 38.</note> under the notion of first fruits and lump, root and branches, as if the temple at Jerusalem were the one, and our Christian Churches the other.</p>
            <p>Having thus produced our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, for the holiness of our Christian Churches, it is now expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to explain what kind of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness it is which we affirm to be in these places, the right apprehension whereof will put fair (if men will be satisfied) to the end of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie in this matter.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Holy,</hi> is of a various sense, and signification, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny restraining to one, to wit, that holiness which is by the sanctifying grace of Gods holy spirit, whereof the material house of God not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing capable, they cannot therefore conceive how it should be holy.</p>
            <p>The Greek hath two words for holy, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; this latter is commonly applyed to the Temple, which is called in scripture, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the holy place: though sometimes the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly used in another sense, is given to the Temple, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.15. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170261:47"/>having also two words, <hi>Sacer,</hi> and <hi>Sanct us,</hi> useth them also as the Greeks do theirs: And how either of these words may be applyed to the house of God, may be cleared by this distinction: that there is a three-fold holiness, Primitive, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivative, and Relative. The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive holiness belongeth to God alone, who is holy in himself; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness being an essential, pertaining to his divine nature, eternal, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>separable: whence the blessed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels which wait about his throne, cry continually,
<note place="margin">Isa. 6.3. Reu. 4.8.</note>
               <hi>Holy, holy, holy,</hi> is the Lord of hosts. No creature ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heaven, or earth, is holy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, Gods essential ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse being incommunicable. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, There is a derivative ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, which properly belongeth to the reasonable creature, Angels and men they only being capable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: this is wrought by the power of Grace, bringing them into a simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, and likeness with God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them holy, as he is holy: though there may be some difference betwixt Angels, and men, both in respect of the quality, and also of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170261:47"/>the degree of holiness, Angels ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it in an higher measure then men, and theirs being natural, they retaining still that holinesse where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were first created; and mans being restaurative, and (as we may say) at the second hand, which is not much to be stood upon in this place. Thirdly, There is a Relative holinesse, which every thing hath that is dedicated to Gods worship and service, and which, by such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication becommeth Gods: And this is the holiness which we ascribe unto our Churches, as having a nearer relation unto God, then profane or common places may challenge. As we see in persons, that some are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated unto God, and so become his more peculiarly, then they were before, by Gods universal propriety; and so are called unto holinesse: So (the comparison is St. <hi>Austins</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) may we say of places, that such as are separated from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon use to the service of God, have a kind of regeneration passed upon them, whereby they pertake of this Relative holinesse: for, having such relation to God, as the recording
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170261:48"/>his name upon them, their being called his houses, and dedicated to his service, they may justly be called and accounted holy.</p>
            <p>And this giveth Churches the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminency above all the stately build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the world; Let Eustathians, and Fratricellians belch out against them such unworthy comparisons as I shall not foil my paper with; the stateliest royall palace that ever was inhabited by any earthly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, the most glorious chamber of presence that ever was dignified with the throne of human Majestie, may not compare with one of Gods houses. And the voice speaking to the mountains, <hi>Psal.</hi> 68.16. Why leap ye, ye high hills? This is the hill which God desireth to dwell in: (for the fruitful mountains of <hi>Basan</hi> had not such cause to leap and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, as mount <hi>Sion</hi> had) will say as much for the house of God: Why do ye magnificent structures of earthly Kings, exalt your selves for your richness, glory, and beauty? This is Gods house, of more hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable relation then you by far, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenished with treasures, inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170261:48"/>transcending yours, and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the glorious rayes of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine presence, which you could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver show. And surely, they, whose religious hearts God hath wrought to an upright apprehension of the quality of his house, do from hence admire, and cry out with <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 84.1. How amiable are thy tabernacles, <hi>O Lord of hosts? Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> not onely in respect of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward splendor and beauty, which certainly is not displeasing, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth the devout liberality of his people in taking care for the decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his dwelling place, and would also be an external motive, <hi>affectus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin. in</hi> Psa. 27.4.</note>
               <hi>&amp; vota fidelium ad se rapere,</hi> to draw the affections of the faithful to a devout contemplation of the place. Though this be so much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by too many, that they care not how sordidly and sluttishly the house of God lyeth,
<note place="margin">Act. 19.35.</note> which thing they will not endure in their own houses: <hi>Diana</hi> shall have her <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, such worshippers as will keep her temple comely, and handsome, whilest the true God shall have few
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170261:49"/>that will take care for his: Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> praiseth <hi>Nepotian</hi> being dead,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Heliod.</hi>
               </note> that he was careful the altar should look bright, the walls of the Church should be without dust and cobwebs, and the pavement cleane swept; which cleansing is a kind of sanctification of Gods house, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29.16, 17, 18. But it is to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that too many now living in the world, will not leave behind them this commendation, that their name may be precious to posterity. But <hi>Amiable</hi> also in respect of those spiritual excellencies with which it is endowed, that divine and angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal presence wherewith it is frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, those heavenly priviledges which God by his Divine Charter hath conferred upon it: These make the house of God more <hi>Amiable</hi> then the royal'st Seraglio in the world. And well may the house of God have this esteem amongst men, when surely it is so with God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
<note place="margin">Psal. 87.2</note> who, as he loved the gates of Sion more then all the dwellings of <hi>Jacob,</hi> so he beareth a dearer affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and respect to the houses called by his Name, and dedicated to his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170261:49"/>service, then he doth to any other buildings whatsoever.</p>
            <p>Thus having spoken of the house of God simply by it self, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the next: Having said what is necessary for the information of our judgement, we shall take into consideration the things conducing to practice, whereof the first is our access to the house of God, implyed in the word, <hi>Goest.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>When thou goest.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>COncerning this Access unto, and visitation of, the house of God; It is the best piece of service that our feet can do us, to carry us to this holy place, and there are no footsteps so well spent, as those in resorting thither: and how good a thing would it be,
<note place="margin">1 King. 2.2</note> if the words of <hi>David,</hi> I go the way of all the earth, were true in this sense, that it were the generall practice of the world, to visit the dwelling place of the true and only God?
<note place="margin">Joh. 12.31 2 Cor. 4.4.</note> Then would not the Devill be the prince of this world, nor the god of this world, but his kingdom would be trampled
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170261:50"/>under foot, and his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Ignatius ad Ephes.</note> his fiery darts of sinne wherewith he so much poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soneth the world, would all be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, and extinguished. Then would religion raign inwardly in mens hearts, and flourish outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in holy and righteous actions. This the Devill knoweth well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and therefore is he busie to instil poisonous infections into mens judgements concerning the nature of Gods house, and to cast impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the way whereby to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them in their due addresses thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: nay, to suggest arguments unto them, whereby to defend the omission and wilful neglect of this holy practice. Sometimes he telleth them that God is omnipresent, as well in one place as another, that he is no respecter of places, but all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to him alike; which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he put into <hi>Jeroboams</hi> head, who (as <hi>Josephus</hi> witnesseth) used it to withdraw the Israelites from serving God in his appointed tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at Jerusalem, to worship the calves which he had set up in <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel:</hi> the common argument
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170261:50"/>which is used by many in these our days. And when the subtle serpent hath beguiled men with this deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful argument, making them to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and despise all addresses to the house of God; his next step is to instigate and exasperate them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such as desire to be religious, to scoffe at these, to revile, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne them, endeavouring by this means, either to impede accesses to Gods house, or to root out the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons who desire to retain the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practice thereof. <hi>Murmurant iniqui, &amp; ingrati, &amp; illo nefario spiritu, altius obstrictius{que} oppressi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 28</note>
                  <hi>quòd populi confluunt ad ecclesias casta celebritate:</hi> Wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful men, being more deeply and straitly bound by that wicked spirit, do murmur, because the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God flow to their Churches with a chast celebrity. Religion is the devils eye-sore, and this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular duty of frequenting Gods house, as great a mote in his eye as any other; no marvel then, if he chafe at this way, and both by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self and instruments oppose and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct it all he can. We read, that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170261:51"/>God himself was twice an hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to his peoples entring into his dwelling place, <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.34, 35. and 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.10.11. For such was the extraordinary manifestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods presence at those times, that it would have been high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption for any, even for <hi>Moses</hi> and the priests themselves to have attempted entrance: when, like the flie approaching too near the flame, they might have been consumed by the fire of divine indignation: But how often doth Satan with his wiles hinder men in the pursuance of this religious practice? how many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments doth he cast in their way? how many excuses doth he furnish them withal? Like those in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. Sometimes matters of profit, sometimes pleasures and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, sometimes they are indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, sometimes they cannot, sometimes they will not go to Gods house,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Guber. lib.</hi> 6.</note>
                  <hi>Nos ecclesiis Dei ludicra an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teponimus, &amp;c. Spernitur Dei tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum, &amp; coucurritur ad theatrum,</hi> as <hi>Salvianus</hi> complained. We pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serre sports before the Churches of God, the temple of God is despised,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170261:51"/>and we run to the Theatre. But any of these things are so far from excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing us, as that they shall rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us before God, who for this neglect will kindle his wrath against us, as he did against the house of <hi>Judah,</hi> and inhabitants of Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.16. For how can we think, that God should bear the contempt of so great mercy? Mercy I call it, for so it is, and a very great mercy too, that God should vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe his people a set place for his worship, with liberty and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of making their addresses thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for, when God promised his return to Jerusalem with mercies, the first and chiefest particular in his promise, was, that his house should be built, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.16. as if all other blessings were the attendants and consequents of this. And this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he hath vouchsafed unto, and for a long time continued upon us, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying it to many places and ages, farre more zealous and religious then we: the Saints in other ages, and places being persecuted and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished from the publique service of God, have been constrained to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170261:52"/>it in woods, and deserts, in dens and caves of the earth, and many times in their owne private dwellings to assemble themselves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, like the Disciples, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.19. for fear of their enemies, that in comparison of our dayes of freedom with theirs of restraint, we may take up our Saviours words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.17. Many Prophets, and righteous men have desired to see those things which we see, and have not seene them. King <hi>David</hi> apprehended it as a great mercy from God, when by reason of <hi>Absaloms</hi> conspiracy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing driven from Jerusalem, and <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dok</hi> the priest taking the Ark with him, <hi>David</hi> commanded <hi>Zadok</hi> to carry it back againe, making this conclusion to himself, If I shall find favour in the eyes of the Lord,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15 25.</note> he will bring me againe, and shew me, both it, and his habitation: God hath not so separated betwixt his house and us, but he sheweth us his dwelling place, and giveth us liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of making addresses thereunto; yet we consider it not that we might make ourselves a delight unto him: We neglect his house, and passe-by
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170261:52"/>hours of Gods publique service, as if they were but of indifferent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity. And it were but just with God, if, for this our neglect, he should bereave us of this mercy, by setting over us a wicked <hi>Ahaz,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 24.28. <hi>Neph. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> that should cause our Temple doors to be shut up, or a cruel <hi>Dioclesian;</hi> that should enact our Churches to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled with the ground: and Gods anger to be greater yet in depriving us of entrance hereafter into his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly habitation: Nor can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect other at Gods hand, then here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be excluded from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Gods presence there: for, if we refuse to enter into Gods earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly house when the doors are open, how can we hope to enter into his heavenly house, when the doors are shut?
<note place="margin">Luk. 13.25.</note> If we will not enter when we may, we shall not enter when we would.</p>
               <p>If then any of us have been slack in this duty heretofore, let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the more diligent hereafter: If we have despised, or hated the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place, let us reverence and love it the more; as once God appointed an attonement, and reconciliation
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170261:53"/>of his house to himself, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.16. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.21, 22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45.20. So let us be reconciled to it, both in our affection, and practice of due frequenting, rejoycing with devout <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 122.1.</note> when they say unto us, We will go into the house of the Lord. This we would most cheerfully do, if we considered the benefits which thereby would accrew unto us: Gods house is his fountain, his treasury, his shop, where all bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings corporal and spiritual are to be obtained at his hands: If we want the knowledge of God, and his wayes, Gods house is a School, and God himself our teacher, <hi>Isa.</hi> 2.3. And thither did <hi>David</hi> repair for resolution in that which did so much puzzle him, to wit, the pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of wicked men, <hi>Psal.</hi> 73.16, 17. If we have enemies that threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us, Gods house is a Sanctuary, whither king <hi>Hezekiah</hi> resorted to procure Gods protection against <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.14. What ever else we want, is there to be had, for God is ready to impart his good things unto us. Although it be true, that God doth every day dispense
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170261:53"/>his heavenly commodities, as it were by retail, to a petitioner that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his private closet; yet in his house he imparteth them by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sale, many things to many persons atonce the fatnesse of which house shall abundantly satisfie every one that desireth to partake thereof.
<note place="margin">Psa. 36.8</note>
               </p>
               <p>And on the contrary, to the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Gods house, the abundance of iniquity that now raigneth amongst the generality of men, may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted; swearing, lying, pride, envy, malice, drunkennesse, fornication, disobedience, blood, &amp;c. because men care not for visiting Gods courts, that he may keep them from these sinnes, and bestow upon them such graces and virtues, as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. There was no other reason of <hi>Thomas</hi> his wanting faith to believe the resurrection of Christ,
<note place="margin">Joh. 20.44.</note> then his not being with the other Apostles when Christ appeared unto them; for had he then been with them, he had believed as they did.</p>
               <p>Thus having seen the necessity of visiting Gods house, in the word, <hi>Goest;</hi> we shall enter upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of the third and last thing,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170261:54"/>to wit, The manner of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse, shewing how we ought to prepare, and demean our selves, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the purport of the words, <hi>Keep thy foot. Solomons</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were careful to give him reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious education: his mother did her part, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.1. The prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie which his mother taught him. But this of an holy address to the house of God,
<note place="margin">1 Chro. 28.</note> he learned from his father <hi>David,</hi> who not only instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and encouraged him in the building of the temple, but also gave him example of a right ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress thereunto by his own religious practice, which he expresseth in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusion to this of <hi>Solomon, Psal.</hi> 26.12. My foot standeth in an eeven place, I will praise God in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. Before he would adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to joyn himself with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique assembly to praise God, he would see that his foot should stand upright. Not that he looked so much to his bodily foot, but to his whole selfe, soul and body, with all that belonged thereunto: for so the word <hi>foot</hi> doth commonly signifie in scripture, as goings, and footsteps
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170261:54"/>signifie our wayes. And how necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>David</hi> thought a due preparation to the house of God to be, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by that prayer of his, <hi>Psal.</hi> 43.3.4. that God would send out his light, and his truth: And to what end? To lead him, and bring him unto Gods holy hill, and to his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles; then would he go to the altar of God, &amp;c. Gods light, to give us a true understanding of the duty of going to his house; and truth, to enable us with a practicall performance of such qualifications as are necessary thereunto, are things worthy that we should pray for them.</p>
               <p>Now, the better to understand the particular qualifications of our duty herein, we shall dispose them into three sorts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Such as are necessary when we go, or enter.</item>
                  <item>2. Such as are necessary whilst we continue there.</item>
                  <item>3. Such as are necessary when we depart, and go out thence.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The necessary when we go, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Gods house, are four.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Zeal.</hi> This is the spirit that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170261:55"/>giveth life and motion both to soul and body, when we visit Gods courts; without this we come but like dead men, and so are like to offer but dead sacrifices: which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> not being ignorant of, would frame his heart to a due preparative temper, before he appeared before God in his house;
<note place="margin">Psa. 26.8, 44, 2.</note> Lord, I have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the habitation of thy house, and the place where thine honour dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. My soul longeth, yea even fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for the courts of the Lord. When <hi>Abraham</hi> went to offer up his son <hi>Isaac,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 22.6</note> he took fire along with him: such a fire is Zeal which actuates the sacrifice, making it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God, who is so much the more pleased, by how much the fire of zeal is the more fervent. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other things which the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> saw in <hi>Solomons</hi> court, which so wrought upon her admiration, that there was no more spirit in her,
<note place="margin">1 Kin. 10.5.</note> one was the ascent whereby King <hi>Solomon</hi> went up to the house of the Lord: A zealous and fervent address to Gods house highly takes with God himself, and his holy Angels, heaven it selfe is
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170261:55"/>warmed with delight at the fire of true zeal, in the hearts of such as come into Gods house. It is not for us then to come with cold and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen hearts, no nor with a lukewarm indifferency, but with hearts zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously affected to converse with God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Holiness;</hi> Which is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in regard we go to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy God, who will be san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in all that come nigh him:
<note place="margin">Levit. 20.3.</note> and seeing God is holy, the duties holy, the place holy, there is great reason the persons should be holy also. <hi>Jacob</hi> knew full well how necessary clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing was before an appearance before God; therefore he commanded his family to make themselves cleane, and then to go up to <hi>Bethel, Gen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 30.20, 21.</note> 35.2, 3. The Priests under the law washed themselves before they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred in their office; so it befitteth every one that intendeth to visit Gods courts, to cleanse himselfe from the filthiness of sin and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; a thing which holy <hi>David</hi> was careful to do, <hi>Psal.</hi> 26.6. I will wash mine hands in innocency, so will I compass thine altar, O Lord With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this washing, a man is not fit to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170261:56"/>come into Gods presence, who will be more highly displeased with such impure intrusions,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 27</note> then <hi>Achish</hi> king of <hi>Gath</hi> could be with <hi>Davd,</hi> when he connterfeited madnesse before him, letting the spittle fall upon his beard. And we find Gods displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure upon record, wherein he sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebuked his people Israel for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming to enter into his house, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so unqualified through their sins, <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.9.10. Will ye steal, murder, and commit adultery, and swear falsly, and burn incense unto <hi>Baal.</hi> and walk after other gods whom ye know not; and come and stand before me in this house which is called by my name? And again, <hi>Ier.</hi> 11.15. What hath my beloved to do in mine house, seeing she hath wrought lewdness with many? He chargeth them likewise by <hi>Ezekiel, Chap.</hi> 23.39. When they had slain their children to their Idols, then they came the same day into my san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary to profane it, and lo, this they have done in the midst of mine house. This is the grand pollution of Gods house; though the other, the employing it to secular affaires,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170261:56"/>be bad enough, as our Saviour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked the Jews for making his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers house an house of merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, a den of theeves,
<note place="margin">Joh. 2.16. Mat. 21.19.</note> yet to come with feet defiled with the filth of sin this is well worse: for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduceth only human affairs, else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where lawful, but this brings in the works of the devil, no where law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: And how can God take this? If the Jews themselves should be so jealous of their temple; that they denyed entrance to a Gentile, and therefore persecuted St.
<note place="margin">Act 21.29</note>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> upon a supposal of his bringing in <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phimus</hi> an <hi>Ephesian;</hi> how may God himself be incensed, if men having the devil, and his works upon them, shall bring them into his house? nay, do we not find God himself mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festing his dislike, when his own people brought into his sanctuary strangers uncircumcised in heart, and uncircumcised in flesh, to be in his sanctuary to pollute it, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.7? How much more then will the bringing in of Satan, and his works, dislike him? Let us then look to our feet, that we may have them holy at our entrance into Gods
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170261:57"/>house. 'Tis strange to see how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful we are of our bodies, and the garments wherewith we are cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: they must be in all points of neatness, and handsomness, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, <hi>A la mode:</hi> we wash, we brush, we consult with our looking-glass. striving to prevent shame in the sight of men, and as St. <hi>Austin</hi> speaks, <hi>Si macula in veste, aut cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore apparet, non audes intrare; si vero sordida mens &amp; conscientia, nihil times:</hi> If a spot appear in our garments, or faces, we are afraid to enter; but if we have a mind never so sordid, a conscience never so pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, we fear nothing: we set lesse by shame, and rebuke in the sight of God, then of men; and prefer out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward decency in our appearance to human presence, before the beauty of holiness in our hearts in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God, and his holy Angels. We should not be thus ill affected, thus stupidly insensible, thus rashly presumptuous towards Gods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine presence: But, as holiness be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth Gods house, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have applyed to the place; so here we may also fitly apply it to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170261:57"/>our persons, to our hearts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences when we come into it. Even Heathens who were any thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout in their idolatrous worship, would teach this at their entrance into their Temples.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pers. Sat.</hi> 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Compostum jus, fas{que} animo, sanctos{que} recessus Mentis, &amp; incoct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um generoso pectus honesto. Haec cedo ut admoveam templis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Reverence.</hi> This is twofold; Spiritual, and Corporal. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual is an awful and dreadful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of the heavenly Majesty of God before whom we present our selves: and is necessary in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that infinite disproportion which is betwixt God and us: He, the Great and glorious God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth; We, dust and ashes;
<note place="margin">Psal. 2.11</note> He, the Creator; We, the poore Creatures. Therefore ought we to serve him with fear, and rejoyce with trembling. We must take heed that we be not surprized with such heedlesness, as to say with <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 28.16. Surely the <hi>Lord</hi> is in this place, and we know it not, but
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170261:58"/>to remember what he said upon his better thoughts, How dreadful is this place, this is none other but the house of God. And if <hi>Iosephs</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were afraid, being brought into <hi>Iosephs</hi> house, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43 18. We, upon due consideration of our selves, have more cause to feare, when we come into the house of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, There is a Corporall reverence to be practised as well as the other, and that is in presenting our selves after an humble manner with bodily adoration unto God, before whom we make our appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. This is as much Gods due, as any other duty belonging unto him from us: And if we present our selves before his Majesty, as <hi>Deuca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> and <hi>Pyrrha</hi> are described to have done to their goddesses.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Procumbit vter{que}</l>
                  <l>Pronus humi,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ovid. Met.</hi> 1.</note> gelido{que} pavens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit oscula saxo.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Both of them fell prostrate upon the ground, as it were kissing the stones: Or, as the Emperour <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170261:58"/>entred the Church at <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain,</hi> prostrate upon the ground,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodorat. Hist. Ecc. l.</hi> 5.</note> using those words, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.25. <hi>Adhaesit pavimento.</hi> My soul clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth unto the ground: Or, as those devout Christians in <hi>Salvianus</hi> his time,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>mihi p.</hi> 226</note>
                  <hi>Ad domus Dominicas curri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, corpora humi sternimus,</hi> We run to Gods houses, we straw our bodies upon the ground: I know not who (unless the profaner sort of men) would condemn us for it. God himself would not, for he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth bodily adoration at our hands, nor the devout saints of God, for they invite, and incite one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Psal.</hi> 95 6. O come let us wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and fall down, and kneel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord our Maker. Nay, this ought to be considered in our going to Gods house, that it ought to be one main end thereof; therefore the ancient Church resolved,
<note place="margin">Psa. 132.7</note> We will go into his tabernacles, we will worship at his footstool: And ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David</hi> going thither, performed this duty, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.20. He came into the house of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and worshipped: Whether at that time
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170261:59"/>he did any thing else, we will not enquire, but this of adoration he did, and if he did no more then worship, it was surely accepted of God. <hi>Elkanah</hi> the Father of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> went yearly to Jerusalem to worship:
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.3.</note> And although the word <hi>worship</hi> there may imply in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral sense, whatsoever service was then to be performed, as necessary (the word being in many places of scripture taken in the largest sense) yet the Text seemeth to restrain it to this particular of bodily adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if this were, (if not the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet) the chiefest end of <hi>Elka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi>'s going thither. He went, <hi>ut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doraret,</hi> saith the vulgar Latine, That he might worship: But <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> more cleerly, and neerly, <hi>ad incurvandum,</hi> that he might crook or bow his body to God, as the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal implyeth. If then the devout people of God have made this a principal end of their going to Gods house; Why should not we also do the same? Is it enough to say, We go to hear, or to pray? Must we be all on the taking hand with God,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170261:59"/>and never on the giving?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> John Fox <hi>the famous compiler of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Church Chronicles though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise no confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist to the discipline and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, yet he is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted never to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred any Church without expressing solemn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence therein. M.</hi> Fuller <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 76.</note> And what shall we give, if not bodily wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, which is as sutable with the Majestie of God, as agreeable with his revealed will, and as acceptable in his sight, as any other service per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by us in his house. So that we will not fear to say, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever resolveth to make his address to Gods house, and doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the performance of an humble bodily adoration, to be one of those ends for which he goeth thither, he doth not go so prepared and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified as he ought to be: he consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth not aright, either God, or himself, and so doth not <hi>take heed to his foot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is worthy to be considered by us, how that our acceptation, or rejection at Gods hand, dependeth upon our deportment before him, therefore we cannot but think an humble and sincere bodily adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be a principall means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing Gods favour, and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a rude rushing into his divine presence, a provocation of his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure. The two captains which
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170261:60"/>came to the prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 1.9.10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> in a bold and saucy way; Thou man of God, the King hath said, Come downe, met with fire from heaven, which consumed them and their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, for their peremptory way of demanding: when he that came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a lowly manner, found favour, and was not onely spared, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his request: And why this (by way of similitude) should not be appliable to us when we come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods house, to present our selves there before his terrible Majesty, I know no reason.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Corn. Agripa. de occult. Philosoph. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> For, as one saith, <hi>Nihil Deo magis displicet, quàm neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligi, quàm contemni; nihil magis placet, quàm venerari, quàm ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari:</hi> Nothing doth more displease God, then to be neglected, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned; and nothing doth more please him, then to be reverenced and adored. A cleare testimony whereof may seem to have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<note place="margin">Rev. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1</note> when a holy Angel command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed St. <hi>John</hi> to measure the Temple, and them that worshipped therein; signifying that both the place, and persons were so respected by God,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170261:60"/>as that his provident care should be over them, to preserve them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth thing, necessary in our going into the house of God, is Humility; that we devest our selves of all opinion of merit and worthiness to come before his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, attributing those gracious opportunities to Gods free grace and mercy. Holy <hi>David,</hi> a man after Gods own heart, might as far have pleaded his own worth to enter into Gods courts, as ever any might have done; but he knew well enough that this would not do, therefore he resolved to go the other way, <hi>Psal.</hi> 5.7. As for me, I will come into thy house in the multitude of thy mercy. For the best of us all have nothing in our selves, to justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our appearance before God in his house, but the mercy and goodness of God himself, who is pleased to command us this duty, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise his acceptance, otherwise it were high presumption in us, and we might suffer for so doing. Gods presence is more choise, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170261:61"/>than that of those ancient <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian</hi> Monarchs;
<note place="margin">Esth. 4.11</note> but his holding forth the golden Scepter of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, is our warrant and encoura ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What the Centurion said to our Saviour, <hi>Lord,</hi> I am not worthy that thou shouldst come under my roof,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.8.</note> may every one of us convert, and say to God, We are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to come under thy roof, for we have no apparel, no endowments of our own, sutable with thy glorious presence, unless thou please to cover our deformities with thy wings of mercy: If thou hadst not made the posts and doors of thy house of the Olive-tree of mercy and peace,
<note place="margin">1 King. 6.31, 32, 33</note> we should not be able to set our foot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy threshold. These are the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of entrance into Gods house.</p>
               <p>The next are the duties of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance therein.</p>
               <p>When Satan, the enemy of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, seeth, that notwithstanding his temptations to the contrary,
<note place="margin">Iob. 1.6.</note> we are resolved to visit Gods house, then, as in the days of <hi>Iob,</hi> when the sons of God came to present themselves before the Lord, Satan also came
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170261:61"/>among them: So will he go along with men to the house of God,
<note place="margin">Joh. 2.16. Mat. 21.79.</note> to pervert, and disturbe them, that their being there may be fruitless and dangerous, it being his aime, that they should be not onely not the better, but the worse, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into all evill in the midst of the congregation and assembly. Therefore ought we to remember in whose presence we are, Gods,
<note place="margin">Pro. 5.14</note> and his holy Angels, and answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to demean our selves. Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever defects steal at this time upon us, God seeth them, and they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be concealed from him. Some write of the image of <hi>Iuno,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lucian de dea Syria.</note> that it cast a continual eye upon him that came to worship her, <hi>Si adstiteris, te aspicit, si transeas, visu te sequi tur, &amp;c.</hi> If a man stood still, it beheld him, if he passed forward, it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with her eye. But this of an image was an imaginary conceit: 'tis onely true of the only true God, whose eye is so constantly fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every particular passage of our deportment, that nothing passeth from us, of which it doth not take
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170261:62"/>notice. And by sad experience the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, even they do too often find encrochments upon them, where by they are seduced, and perverted in the performance of holy duties in Gods house;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. de Consci. cap.</hi> 6.</note> St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> sensible thereof, doth heavily complain, <hi>Vae mihi, quia ibi pecco, ubi peccata emendare debeo:</hi> Woe is me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I sin even in that place where I ought to amend my sins: So sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is the Serpent in Paradise, Satan in Gods house, that he instilleth his poyson to annull the balme of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. And besides, he hath a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adjutor, a way-ward nature, a flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heart within us, that is not onely weak to bear the burthen of Gods service in his house, but adverse, ready at every turn to snuffe at it, and cry,
<note place="margin">Mal. 1.13.</note> What a weariness is it? and so to turn aside to by-actions, or entertaine what ever is secretly suggested to the heart. Our care therefore must be so much the more, that we suffer not our selves to be carried away with any sinful or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent behaviour, lest we vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the eye of Gods holiness, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170261:62"/>so, like the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> come not to Gods house for the better,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.17.</note> but for the worse, depriving our selves of that mercy which we came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
               <p>The ordering then of our deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before God in his house, may be reduced unto these particulars, that we ought to order
<q>
                     <l>Our thoughts,</l>
                     <l>Our words,</l>
                     <l>Our gestures.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For our thoughts, we must be carefull not to have them wandring and extravagant, but attentive, and fixed upon those duties which we come about. It is a thing much to be desired, and surely by diligent exercise, in an acceptable measure to be obtained, for us to have such command over our hearts, our worldly cares, and thoughts, that as <hi>Abraham</hi> said to his servants,
<note place="margin">Gen. 22.5.</note> Abide ye here with the Ass, and I, the lad, will go yonder and worship, and come again unto you: So, for us to discharge at the present all secular
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170261:63"/>cogitations, untill we go to the house of god; and having perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our duty there, to resume them againe. So that whilest we are in Gods house, our care must be to have our hearts there, and not like the Jews, who drew nigh unto God with their mouth, and honoured him with their lips, but their hearts were far from him: Comming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prophet,
<note place="margin">Isa. 29.13 Ezek. 33.31.</note> as the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and hearing his words; but yet they would not do them, for their heart was gone after their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse. This must needs be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing to God, and not onely as improfitable, but as dangerous to our selves, as if we came not to Gods house at all. And although we be liable, even at this time (and perhaps more especially at this time then others) to many avocations, and diversions of our thoughts, which in the words of St. <hi>Austin</hi> deserve an humble confession, that God may pardon it, <hi>Ausus sum in celebritate solemnitatum tuarum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confes. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>
                  <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra parietes ecclesiae tuae, concupis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, &amp; agere negotium procurandi
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170261:63"/>fructus mortis:</hi> We are bold in the celebration of Gods solemn service, within the walls of his Church, to covet. and to do the work of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing death unto our selves: yet a godly sorrow for it, and a carefull endeavour to avoid it, will be a means of procuring mercy at Gods hand, that our service shall not be so frustrated, but that we shall have his gracious acceptation, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain those blessings which we stand in need of Onely I say, we must keep our hearts with all diligence, shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the door, that no extraneous cogitations may enter; and if either before, at, or after our entrance into Gods house, they shall knock for admission, then to answer them, with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> We are doing a great work,
<note place="margin">Chap 6.3.</note> so that we cannot come down. Why should the work cease, whilest we leave it, and come down to you? Our hearts are now for bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesses of another nature, and we must, with Gods people, thinke of his loving kindness in the midst of his Temple:
<note place="margin">Psa. 48.9.</note> This is a fit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per subject for our hearts to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versant
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170261:64"/>about, whilest we are before God. And this may seem to have been represented in the building of our Churches, where we commonly see the windows built so high from the ground, that one standing upon the ground, cannot look out of them, unless it be to behold the skie; the pious builders intimating thereby, that, as our eyes are contained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in those walls, and debarred from beholding outward objects, so should our hearts be restrained in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our service there before God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We must be carefull of our words, that we abstaine from impertinent discourses and speeches, which in Gods house can scarcely be innocent, though elsewhere they may: If at any time we ought with <hi>David</hi> to keep our mouthes as it were with a bridle;
<note place="margin">Psal. 39.1</note> now especially is the time when we are before God: We must take heed that we grate not Gods ear with breaking the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of holy reverence and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by untuning our tongues with impertinent language, not relating
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170261:64"/>to the duty proper for the place, and presence:
<note place="margin">Psal. 29.9</note> In his temple doth every man speak of his honour. Confession of sinne, thanksgiving, singing of psalms, these are duties quadrant with Gods house and presence, and therefore ought not to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned with idle whisperings, or secular discourses. The <hi>Romans</hi> (though heathens) were carefull to avoid these in their idolatrous so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities; for one, speaking of the cruelty of <hi>Tiberius Caesar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tac.</note> useth these words, <hi>Inter sacra, &amp; vota, quo tempore etiam verbis profanis abstinere mos esset, &amp;c.</hi> Such was the cruelty of that man, that men were seized upon at their solemne devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, at which time it was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome to abstain from prophane and common language. If these people were so carefull of not mingling their secular discourses with their religious rites, should not we Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians take heed of speaking the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Ashdod,</hi> and <hi>Canaan,</hi> or intermixing speeches of other busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, whilest we are before the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true God, in the house which is
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170261:65"/>called by his name? Shall our God be a better God then theirs; and shall we serve him worse then they did theirs? Did they bridle their tongues at the times of their publick devotions, and shall we let ours go loose? No sure: but, as God hath laid a restraint upon our tongues, not to speak our own words upon his sabbath, his holy day, <hi>Isai.</hi> 58.13. So, questionless he doth, that we speak not our own words in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place.</p>
               <p>The third thing requiring our cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspection in Gods house, is our gestures and actions: these ought to be so soberly composed, as to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the inward reverence, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and devotion of our hearts: not loose, or wanton, as the custom of too many is, who consider not where they are. 'Tis a sad thing to see many of our Christians assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies so different and disagreeing in their behaviour, as if, like that rude <hi>Ephesian</hi> rout,
<note place="margin">Act. 19.32.</note> the greater part knew not wherefore they were come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; some gazing about them, some ordering their bravery, some nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170261:65"/>some sporting, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impertinencies, to trifle out the time of divine service. If a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian should go into a Turkish Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, at the time of their solemnities, he should see them otherwise com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, immoveable,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Busbeq. Ep.</hi> 3.</note>
                  <hi>Quasi in solo succrevisse viderentur,</hi> as if they grew to the ground whereon they stood, without making any noise, turnings, or writhings of the body, this way or that way: But, if a Turk should come into one of our Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches, and should behold such a medley of postures, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, as are far discordant from the work we have in hand; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle lets us know what would be his answer; He would say,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 14.23.</note> we were mad: In boasting so much of our Christian Religion, of having the knowledge of the true God, and the only way of his worship; yet we make no semblance thereof, when we are before him in his honse, but as if God were our equall, and we hail fellow well met; we express nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gravity, nor reverence in the presence of his Glory. This is not
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170261:66"/>the way to invite a Turk to embrace our Christian Religion, but rather to make him scorn and detest it.</p>
               <p>And having here an opportunity to takenotice of putting on our Hats in the Church, we shall not let it pass without a word or two. It hath indeed almost a generall approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and practice, and more of late then formerly, for persons of all sorts to do that in the house of God, which they will not dare to do in the private houses of their superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors: the meanest meniall servant will be covered at his Masters elbow in the Church, which, at home (his civility is such) he forbears, so that his earthly Master fares the worse for the presence of his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord. And besides: covering, and uncovering the head, is practised with such partiality in respect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious duties, that if they were cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized about it, could not be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered with any reason: At the singing of a Psalme the head is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and covered at the reading of a Chapter: At the prayer before the Sermon, off goes the hat, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170261:66"/>on again when the Sermon begins: Why there should be this partiall respect to religious duties, I wish some body would satisfie.</p>
               <p>But if we, through the whole ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, be before God in his house, and his presence be any motive to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the head (sure) ought to show it as well as our tongues, knees, hands, or any other member; And if this reverence be to be practised at any religious duty, why should it not be at all? For the service of God which we come about, is either in speaking unto God, or hearing him speak unto us; and, if his spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to us be of as great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as our speaking unto him, why should we not expresse as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence at the Sermon, as at the prayer, at the reading of a Chapter,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr. Forbs Irone cum. p.</hi> 350.</note> as at the singing of a Psalme? We reverence (saith a learned person of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi>) the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the sacred Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Discedite templo, Et velate ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put Ovid, Met.</hi> 1.</note> hearing it with our heads uncovered; that is, honouring God speaking to us, with an adorning gesture. Nor is this more then the Scriptures will
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170261:67"/>justifie: If a man pray, or prophesie with his head covered, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4. he dishonoureth his head; that is, Christ, by whom we have access into Gods presence: And if Christ be thereby dishonoured, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self is so likewise. But the four and twenty Elders would not be guilty of this dishonour, therefore they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crowned their heads, casting their crowns before the throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10. What? was their God of greater glory and majestie then ours? Or, are our hearts better then their crowns? Or, are we in Gods house more accepted to a parity, or fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with God, then those elders were in heaven, that we should not make our heads doe reverence to God as well as they? It is a custom used by the Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi> to make some of their Nobles Grandees and those Grandees are priviledged to put on their hats in the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence. But if men will be Gods Grandees, they must be of their own creation, for God never made them so; though every sordid rustick doth now adays presume upon this,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170261:67"/>and thinks himself a goodly fellow in so doing; yet the four, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Elders would not do it. And certainly the sober Christian doth ever desire, that Gods will may be done in earth, as it is in heaven; that God may be had in reverence by those that stand before him in his earthly house, as he is said to have been by those elders in his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>And so we come in the last place to our <hi>Exitus,</hi> our going out of the house of God. This we must also have a care of, for we may not think that this text brings us to the house, and then leaves us at the threshold, but rather it goes along with us, untill all our service be performed, and we depart from before the Lord: therefore,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 44.5.</note> as the prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was charged to mark well the entring in of the house, with every going forth of the Sanctuary: so this Text of <hi>Salomon</hi> may counsell us to <hi>keep our foot,</hi> not onely at our entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods house, but also at our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth. There was a custome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Jewes, that when the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170261:68"/>high Priest, upon the day of expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, having fulfilled his course, was come out of the Temple, his friends went home with him to make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to congratulate his safe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from the temple: Our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture also deserveth due considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for, as it is Gods mercy that we came into his house; so is it also that we come out in safety, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, if God should be extream, he might consume us upon the place for our unworthiness when we entred, or for our failings when we were there, and so our devotion might have a sad conclusion: Thus God dealt with <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> the sons of <hi>Aaron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 10.</note> they came on, but came not off, for God consumed them by fire: In the like manner fared <hi>Zacharias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.</note> he went into the temple, safe and sound, but came not out so, for he was smitten dumbe: Such measure might God mete unto us, either dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us out of his house in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as he speaks, <hi>Hos.</hi> 9.15. or showing some evident token upon us of his displeasure, for many things which he might lay to our charge,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170261:68"/>both without and within his house; but if we have a safe and happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress, this is Gods mercy, &amp; we may rejoyce at it. The consideration of this, may be one special duty at our going forth of Gods house. To which we may add two more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adoration,</hi> which, as it was the <hi>Aspha,</hi> so, if we make it the <hi>Omega</hi> of our service, no doubt but God will be pleased with it. Humbly on and rudely off, suits not with the dignity of a great man; much lesse with the Majesty of the great God of heaven and earth. Nor is this a new thing, that it should be attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for an innovation: for it was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised in the dayes of king <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> in that famous solemn sacrifice,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 29.28, 29.</note> when, both the King, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation worshipped at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and end of the sacrifice: which, how convenient and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is to be still practised by our Christian assemblies in Gods house, to the honour of God;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Constitut. &amp; Can. of</hi> 1640. <hi>Can.</hi> 7.</note> may appear by the judgement and joynt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of many reverend and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men convened together: who
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170261:69"/>(to use their owne words, which reach higher then their own times) thought it very meet and behoov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and heartily commending it to all good and faithfull people, members of this Church, that they be ready to tender unto the Lord the said acknowledgement, by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reverence and obeysance, both at the comming in, and going out of the said Churches, Chancels, or Chappels, according to the most ancient custome of the Primitive Church, in the purest times, and of this Church also for many years of the raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then; there is evidence for an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-adoration to be performed unto God, and hothing materiall to be said against it; Why may we not, nay, Why should we not practise it, when we go out of Gods house? This our egress may (not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly) be termed the foot of our service, and therefore we ought to take heed to it, as to our foot; in the more proper sense of the text.</p>
               <p>Repentance, and Reformation, is the other thing, that, as we ought
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170261:69"/>to come in holy, so likewise to go out holy, not having contracted new iniquity to our selves in the holy place, nor returning again to our former sinnes, which we left (or ought to have left) behind us;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Salvian. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>mihi p.</hi> 89.</note>
                  <hi>Qui ingreditur ad placandum, non debet egredi, ad exacerbandum,</hi> He that entreth in, to appease God, ought not to go out to provoke him: having purged our selves by our appearing before God in his house, we must not, with the Dog, return to our vomit of sinne againe: having washed our selves, we must not, with the swine, return to our wallowing in the mire; having in Gods house implored, and obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mercy in the deliverance of our souls from former iniquities; we should think, as if God were giving us such a charge, as <hi>Abraham</hi> gave his servant concerning his son <hi>Isaac,</hi> Beware,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.6 Heb. 6.5.</note> that thou bring not my son thither again: Beware you bring not your selves into the land of sinne again, from which I have delivered you: Having in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple tasted the good word of God,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170261:70"/>we should thenceforth stop our ears against all temptations to sinne. Some write,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad richom. pag.</hi> 13. <hi>Num.</hi> 85.</note> that when our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our preached according to that <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.27. He sate upon a stone, and that this stone was never after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards covered with dust, sand, or snow; so clean, and unspotted from the world should we preserve our selves, having been purified in the house of God. The neglect of this, will make us more obnoxious to Gods wrath then we were before; for if we null our late purification in Gods house, 'tis so high a contempt of his mercy, that we shall leave to our selves nothing but a fearfull looking for of judgement, and fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry indignation which will devour us.
<note place="margin">Levit. 23.43, 44, 45.</note> The house which retained the plague, after that the priest had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken pains with it, by taking away the infected stones, scraping the house, and spreading it with new plaister, was adjudged to be pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down, stick and stone, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth out of the city: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, If we shall still retain our old sins, notwithstanding that we have
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170261:70"/>been in Gods house, where God himself, by the ministry of his priest, hath taken pains with us, rebuking our evill wayes, calling us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, offering his mercy, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his justice,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 24.13.</note> directing us how to walk; Thus purging us, and we are not purged: What can we expect but a casting out into outer dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness?</p>
               <p>We see then how neerly it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us, after our performance of holy duties before the holy God, in his holy house, to be carefull of leading a holy life: which if we shall do, that God, whom we have served and worshipped in his house, will open the windows of heaven, and showre his blessings upon us wheresoever we go; As we have been carefull in a devout respect to his house, of our comming in, and going out, so will he preserve our going out, and comming in; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding no good thing from us, and suffering no evill to come nigh us. Thus may God, and we, maintaine a mutuall respect to each other, so long as we live in this world, and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170261:71"/>when God shall please to take us hence, he will bring us into his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly house, where we shall not go forth; but be in the presence of his glory, singing with Angels and Saints, Allelujah's, to his most Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed name, for ever and ever.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tri-Uni Deo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adoratio, Benedictio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In utrâ{que} Dome.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170261:71"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Christian Reader,</hi> If thou art not better furnished, thou mayest, at the taking thy place in Gods house, humbly on thy knees use this short prayer.</head>
            <p>O <hi>My Gracious God, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, I, a poor wretch composed of sinfull dust and ashes, do most humbly beseech thine infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Goodness to forgive my sinnes, which make me unworthy of appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before thy most Holy presence; and to sanctifie me so with thy Grace, that the service which at this time I shall perform unto thee, may be holy and acceptable in thy sight, through Jesus Christ my Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170261:72"/>
            <head>Or this.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Lord, the great God of heaven and earth, which hast com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to come into thine house, there to worship thee, to call upon thy Name, to praise thee for thy benefits, and to hear thy word. Vouch safe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me thy heavenly Grace, that with the spirit of devotion, holiness, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and reverence, I may at this time, be in thy presence, and receive from the riches of thy goodness such things as thou knowest necessary both for my soul and body, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ my Lord and Saviour.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170261:72"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>